<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>[Two notable sermones lately preached at Pauls Crosse Anno 1544]</title>
            <author>Chedsey, William.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1545</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 128 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 78 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2012-10">2012-10 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">B01041</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 5106.5</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S91416</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">52633108</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 52633108</idno>
            <idno type="VID">173926</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. B01041)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 173926)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 2110:1)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>[Two notable sermones lately preached at Pauls Crosse Anno 1544]</title>
                  <author>Chedsey, William.</author>
                  <author>Scott, Cuthbert, d. 1565.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[147+] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>by Johannes Herford, at the costs and charges Robert Toye dwellynge in Paules church yarde, at the sygne of the Bell,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>Jmprynted at London in Aldersgate strete :</pubPlace>
                  <date>Anno dñi 1545.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Title from STC (2nd ed.), imprint from colophon.</note>
                  <note>Second sermon is by Cuthbert Scott--Cf. DNB XVII, 953.</note>
                  <note>Head-piece, tail-piece, initials.</note>
                  <note>Signatures: B-I⁸, K¹⁰.</note>
                  <note>Imperfect: preliminaries lacking. Begins with B₁.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in: Lambeth Palace Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Sermons, English --  16th century.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2011-05</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-05</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>Pip Willcox</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>Pip Willcox</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <body>
         <div type="sermon">
            <pb facs="tcp:173926:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:173926:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <epigraph>
               <q>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Tunc abeuntes phariſei concilium inierunt, vt caperent Ieſum in ſermone.</hi>
                  </p>
               </q>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>Math.</hi> 22.</bibl>
               <q>
                  <p>Then went the phariſees, and toke counſell, howe they myght take Ieſus in his co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>munication.</p>
               </q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>He naturall phi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loſopher Plinius in the .x. boke of his naturall hiſto<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>rye, deſcribinge y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> generation of the Viper, and the maner howe ſhe bryngeth forthe hyr yongeons, ſayth, that the male engendering putteth his heade in the females mouth: whiche heade ſhe for very pleaſure bytyth of. And within .iii dayes after hauyng yongeons in hyr bely, maketh haſt to bring the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> forth. But by reaſon of her ſlacke<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, they can not abyde within
<pb facs="tcp:173926:2"/>
               <pb facs="tcp:173926:2"/>
               <pb facs="tcp:173926:3"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb facs="tcp:173926:3"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb facs="tcp:173926:4"/> her, and gnawynge out hyr belly and ſydes, violently breketh furth with ſlaughter of theyr mother.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Sermo 83 de tempo.</note>What is this els (ſayth ſaynt Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guſtyne) but the very pycture of an enuious perſon: y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> trewe image of a malicious phariſe. The deuil putteth by ſuggeſtyon his head, the ſede of malyce, rankor and en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uye in to mans harte, and by and by ſuch ſwetnes, ſuch pleaſure we co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ceyue of it, that we wyll not ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fre hym to plucke out his head &amp; venyme agayne, but gredely to our vtter deſtruction deuower it. The viper hath yonge within .iii. dayes after hyr conceptio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>: and by<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe ſhe can bringe furth but one at a tyme together, they eate vp hyr belly, &amp; ſo ſhe dyeth. The enui<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ous perſon maketh more ſpede: he co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ceyueth no ſooner, but inco<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tine<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t he feleth ſuch a gnawynge about
<pb facs="tcp:173926:4"/> his harte &amp; ſydys, that yf he kepe one hower or .ii. his venemous ba<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>be within him, he wyl braſte belly, harte, &amp; all together. The phary<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſees clokyd with hypocriticall ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lynes, wha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> they harde both olde &amp; yong laudyng &amp; prayſyng Chryſt with this melodious ſonge:<note place="margin">Mat. 21.</note> 
               <hi>Oſan na filio dauid:</hi> ingenderinge with the deuyll conceyued malyce, and brought furth indignatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, ſaieng: <hi>Audis quid iſti dicu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t?</hi> But here they were ſone quayled by the teſtymo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> lawe: Haue you not redde (ſayth Chriſt) by the mouth of ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bes &amp; ſuckelynges,<note place="margin">Pſal. 2.</note> thou haſte or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deyned thy prayſe? This, foyne could not kepe them backe, but at him they go agayn, &amp; imperyouſly demaunde him, by what power or authorite he droue furth y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> byers &amp; ſellers out of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> te<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ple, why he dyd ouerthrow the tables of the mony
<pb facs="tcp:173926:5"/>
               <pb facs="tcp:173926:5"/>
               <pb facs="tcp:173926:6"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb facs="tcp:173926:6"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb facs="tcp:173926:7"/> exchaungers, and the ſeates of th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> doue ſellers. And here to ſhew (a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> Salomon ſayth) that there is n<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> wyſedome,<note place="margin">Pro. 21.</note> nor prudency, nor cou<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſell able to preuayle agaynſt god he aſking them agayne the queſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>on of Ihons baptiſme, when<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> it was, ether fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> heaue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, or of men and they aunſweringe, they cold not tel, herde likewiſe of Chriſt <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> theyr confuſion: Neyther I wy<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> tell you, by what authorytie I d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> theſe thinges. Beſide thoſe quic<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> aunſwers, the parables folowin<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> dyd byte them, and ſore kyndl<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> theyr anger, when he compary them to that ſonne, which promy<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſed his father to go into his vy<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>yarde, but went not: wherevppo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> he inferrethe, that the publycan and harlettes ſhall come into t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> kyngedome of god, before the<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> Agayne he propoſyth the parab<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb facs="tcp:173926:7"/> of the houſeholder, which had left his ſeruauntes in his vyneyarde: &amp; whan he ſent to haue the frutes of hit, they bette, ſtoned, &amp; kylled his meſſaungers. And at the laſt, put his owne ſonne to deth. What wyll the mayſter of the houſehold (ſayth Chriſte) do to thoſe murde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rers? Here they conde<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ne the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſelues when they geue this ſentens: He wyll cruelly deſtroy thoſe perſons &amp; wyll let out his vyneyarde to o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther men, which ſhall delyuer him y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> fruites at times co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>uenient. Vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> this anſwer chriſt co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>cludith. Ther<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>fore ſay I to you: the kingdome of god ſhalbe taken from you, &amp; ſhal be geuen to other, who ſhall bring forth y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> fruytes of it. Thoſe, &amp; ſuch lyke thinges ſpoken in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> reproche of the chefe preſtes and pharyſeis ſore greuyd them. Theſe ſtyckes made a burnyng fyre in theyr har<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes:
<pb facs="tcp:173926:8"/> in ſo much y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> they wolde hau<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> ſet violently handes vpon Chriſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> yf they had not feared the peopl<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> Neuertheles, they co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tinued fer<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> in theyr pourpoſe. They lyke th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſty horſe leches, &amp; inſatiable blou<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> ſuckers, wyl not leaue the ſkynn<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> vntyl their bellies be ful of blou<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>Non miſſura cutem,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Oratiꝰ de arte poeti<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ca.</note> 
               <hi>niſi plena cruo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> hirudo.</hi> Then after al thoſe waye proued, and nothynge brought paſſe, they vſeth circumuention and diſſimulyng theyr malyce, v<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>der y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> pretence of holynes &amp; iuſtic<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> dyd as y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> goſpel this day teache<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> vs.<note place="margin">Euangel. Math. 22.</note> Then went the phariſees, a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> toke counſell how they myght ta<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>gle Ieſus in his communicatio<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> And they ſent to hym theyr diſc<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ples, with the Herodians, ſayen<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> Mayſter we knowe that thou a trewe, and teacheſte the waye god trewly: Neyther careſt th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb facs="tcp:173926:8"/> for any man: for thou conſydereſt not mens eſtate. Tell vs therfore: howe thynkeſt thou? Is it lawful to paye trybute to Caeſar or no? Ieſus perceyuyng theyr wycked<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, ſayde: Why tempte you me ye Hypocrites? Let me ſe the try<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bute mony: And they toke hym a peny: and he ſayd to them: Whoſe image is this, and ſuperſcriptio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>? They ſayd to him: It is Caeſars. Then ſayd Chriſt: Geue and pay therfore to Ceaſar, that whiche is Ceaſars: and to god, that whiche is goddes.</p>
            <p>¶To declare this to goddes ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nor, and to the comfort of this ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>norable audience, before we procede any further, let vs by prayer call for grace.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="sermon">
            <pb facs="tcp:173926:9"/>
            <epigraph>
               <q>
                  <p>Tunc abeuntes phariſei conciliu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ini<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>runt vt caperent Ieſum in ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mone.</p> 
                  <bibl>Mat. 22.</bibl>
               </q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">W</seg>Yſedome it is, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore a man begyn or enterpryſe any matter, to take counſel: and after counſell taken in dewe tyme to ſette vppon it. This leſſon gaue y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> wiſe man to his ſo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ne:<note place="margin">Eccleſi. 32.</note> 
               <hi>Fili, ſine conſilio ni hil facias, et poſt factu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> non paenitebis</hi> Sonne do nothinge without cou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſell, and than it ſhall neuer repent the of thy deed. But in as moche as there be dyuers kyndes of mat<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ters, ſomme good ſomme badde: Some cou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>celyng to the beſt: ſome to the wurſt: great wareneſſe &amp; di<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ligent circumſpection ought to be vſed, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> we deceyue not our ſelues eyther in raſſhe enterpriſe of mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters
<pb facs="tcp:173926:9"/> or i<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> vnaduiſed delect &amp; choyſe of oure counſelers. To this I maye apply &amp; that not amyſſe, the ſayeng of ſaynt Ihon<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>: <hi>Chariſſimi,</hi>
               <note place="margin">1. Ioan. 4</note> 
               <hi>no lite credere omni ſpiritui ſed pro bate ſpu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s ſi ex deo ſint.</hi> Dere belo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued, beleue not euery ſpirite, take not euery matter that co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>myth to hand, beleue not euery man y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueth you counſel, but fyrſt proue &amp; examyne the matter whether it be good or badde: try your cou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſelers whether they be of god or no. Yf y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> matter be neuer ſo good, and the counſel nought, the noughtyneſſe of the counſel, deſtroyeth the good<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>neſſe of the matter.<note place="margin">2. Reg. 10.</note> Anon kyng of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Ammonites toke a good matter in hand, when he purpoſyd (as his part was) to haue receyued hono<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rably y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> embaſſadours, y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> were ſent to him from kynge Dauyd, to co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort him vppon the dethe of his fa<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ther.
<pb facs="tcp:173926:10"/> But ſe what yll counſell dothe: perſuaſion was made to Anon, that Dauyd hadde ſentte<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> thoſe menne of his, as ſpyes: to vewe his countrey, and ſo to fynde occaſyon craftely to come vpon Anon, and to ſubdewe hym, And vppon that, he contumely<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſly ſentte them backe agayne, ſhamefully diſgyſed: halfe ſha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uynge theyr beardes, and lea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uynge the other halfe vnſhauen: cuttynge of theyr robes and ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parell by the harde buttockes.</p>
            <p>But this ſpytfulneſſe of his, ſca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ped not vnpunyſſhed: for not longe after, he gatherynge an hooſte, entendynge to fyghte a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaynſte Dauid, loſte his hooſte, his menne deſtroyed, and all to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether came to naughte.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">3. Reg. 12.</note>Kynge Roboam went aboute a good matter, when he thoughte
<pb facs="tcp:173926:10"/> vppon the diſpoſition of his re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>alme, &amp; what aunſwer he myghte make to Hieroboam and to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> mul<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tytude that were gathered with hym. But folowynge the lyghte counſell of the yonger ſorte, and reiectynge the ſage counſell of the elders: where as he thoughte to make all, he marde all: loſynge at one tyme. x. trybus of his empyre. Of the other parte, yf a mannes matter be naughte, and his coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſell good, the wyſedome of his counſell ſhall eyther cauſe hym to leue of his naughty matter, and ſo no more to medle with hit, or elles by wyſedome and pollycie, they ſhall qualyfie the thynge.</p>
            <p>When Dauyd fledde the perſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cution of his ſonne Abſolon,<note place="margin">2. Reg. 16.</note> one of Sauls ſtocke called Semei, mette with hym, and curſynge and bannynge, hurled ſtones
<pb facs="tcp:173926:11"/> at Dauyd, haynouſly cryeng. <hi>Egre<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>dere Egredere vir ſanguinu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> et vir Beli al.</hi> Come forth come forth y<hi rend="sup">u</hi> bloud<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>dy man and thou man of Belyal. Abiſai one of dauids cheife ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uauntes was ſore offended with this outrage, and ſtreyght waye wolde haue ben auenged vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> him ſayenge: <hi>Quare maledicit canis hic moriturus domino meo regi? vadam et amputabo caput eius.</hi> Why doth this dogge which by and by ſhall dye, blaſpheme my lord the kyng? I wyll go and cutte of his heade. But kynge Dauyd ſtayde this fers purpoſe of his, with this wiſe counſell. <hi>Dimitte eu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> vt maledicat, dominus enim precepit ei, vt maledi ceret Dauid.</hi> Suffer hym to blaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pheme and curſe, for it is goddes permiſſyon that he ſhal curſe Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uyd for a puniſhment. He interpre<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ted all in the beſte, and ſo ſtayed
<pb facs="tcp:173926:11"/> Abiſais deadly purpoſe. As Ieſꝰ was goinge towarde Hieruſalem about the tyme of his paſſion,<note place="margin">Luc. 9.</note> and ſhulde take Samaria in his myd<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>de way: he ſent before certayne of his diſciples to make prouyſion agaynſt his comming. But y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Sa<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>marytans when they knewe that he was goinge towarde Hieruſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lem, wolde not ſuffer him to come to theyr towne. Iames and Ihon<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> hearinge of this, were ſturred vp to be auenged vppon the Sama<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritans: and commynge to Chriſte, ſayde: <hi>Domine vis dicamus, vt ignis deſcendat, et conſumat illos?</hi> Lorde wylt thou that we commaunde y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> fyer comme downe from heauen, and conſume them? They purpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed death towarde the Samary<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tans: but counſell debated theyr intent, &amp; they herde. <hi>Neſcitis cuius ſpiritus eſtis:</hi> Ye wote not what
<pb facs="tcp:173926:12"/> maner ſpryte ye are of. The ſonne of man is not come to deſtroye, but to ſaue. Nowe yf the matter be good of it ſelfe, and good coun<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſel alſo geuen vpon it, it muſt ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>des turne to a good ende. Lyke as of the contrary ſyde, yf the ma<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ter be naught, and naughty coun<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſell geuen vppon it: it wyll proue ther after. As here it dothe euy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dentely appeare in the phariſees atte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>pt. Their matter was naught they went about to take Ieſus in his communication. Saynt Mat<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>thew ſaith, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>. <hi>Vt illa quear e<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t eu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> in ſermo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>e:</hi> to halter hym in his communica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, or to bryng him in to a ſnare. Saynt Marke,<note place="margin">Mat. 1<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>. <hi>Vt illum venarentur in ſermone:</hi> to hunte hym in his communica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, &amp; to dryue him in to a brake.
<pb facs="tcp:173926:12" rendition="simple:additions"/> And what counſel toke they vpon this matter? They were aſhamed ſo oftentymes confounded to laye this gynne in theyr own perſons: and therfore they ſende as falſe and as crafty as they were them ſelues, which ſhulde brynge with out ſuſpicion this matter to paſſe. <hi>Et mittunt ad eum diſcipulos ſuos cu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> Herodianis.</hi> They ſende to hym theyr diſciples with the Herodi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans.<note place="margin">Lib 1. ca. 22.</note> The holy man Epiphanius in his worke that he maketh <hi>con<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tra octaginta errores,</hi> ſayth, that the Herodians was one of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> hereſyes whiche the Iues hadde amonge theym: beleuynge Herode to be Chryſte becauſe he was the fyrſte ſtraunger that raygned amonge them out of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> trybe of Iuda: &amp; w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> hym agreeth Theophilacte.<note place="margin">Homel. in Math. 21.</note> Ori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>genes ſaith: Peraduenture thoſe
<pb facs="tcp:173926:13"/> which ſayd that the people ough<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> to paye tribut to Ceſar, were cal<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>lyd ſcornefully and in mockayg<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> other part Herodians.<note place="margin">In. 22. Mat.</note> Afte<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> ſaynt Hieromes mynde, they wer<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> Herodesſoudiars. The cauſe wh<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> thoſe Herodians were ſente with the phariſeis diſciples to attemp<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> Chriſt, rather tha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> other, was this Ther was a great co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tention an<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> ſtryfe amonge the Iues whethe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> they beyng the elect &amp; choſen peo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ple of god, hauynge the lawe o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> god ſpecially geuen to them, pay<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>eng theyr tethys and other dew<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tys requyryd in the lawe: whethe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> in this caſe they were bounde <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> pay tribute to Ceaſer or no? An<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> whether they oughte to be ſubie<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>cte to any mans lawes, or no?</p>
            <p>The phariſeys, whiche wolde <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſene not to ſwarue a hears bredt<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> from iuſtyce, in the fauour of th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb facs="tcp:173926:13" rendition="simple:additions"/> people held, that the people of god ſhulde be bounde to no taſkes, nor ought be obedyente to any mans lawes. The Herodians defending the Romayns ryght, ſayd the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary. And to haue this controuer<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſye determyned: yee rather to find an occaſion to trouble chriſte, and to brynge him in daunger, ether to the imperial power (yf he ſhuld ſay that y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> people ought to pay no trybute) ether to the people as de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rogatynge theyr lybertye (yf he ſhulde graunt y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> they were bounde to paye tribute) for this cauſe, I ſay, they ſent wytneſſe ynoughe of both partes: that what ſo euer he ſayde, he ſhulde fall in daunger, Learne the ſubteltye and crafte of the deuyll: He can make thoſe whiche before were deadly enne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies, agree together: that by their agrement innocent bloud myght
<pb facs="tcp:173926:14"/> the rather be ſhedde. There we<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> none ſo extreme enemyes, as we<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> the pharyſeys and y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Herodian<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> but yet to attache chriſt, they con<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſented together, and were well <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> greyd. Greatte enmytie was be<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>twene Pylate and Herode:<note place="margin">Luc. 23.</note> but f<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> that day furthwarde that Pyla<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> ſent Chryſte to be examyned an<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> iudged of Herode, and Herode <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> greate deryſion ſent him backe a<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>gayne: there were none ſo grea<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> frendes as they.<note place="margin">Eccleſi. hi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſto. libro 6. capi. 29</note> Chriſtes ennem<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> Iulianus apoſtata, which had f<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſaken his fayth, and was becom<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> a pagayne, made a lawe that al<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> the temples and churches, which before he had cawſed to be dedy<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ted to falſe Idolles, and to th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> paganyſme, ſhulde be reduced t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> their old forme, and to the chryſt<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> an religion. Ye he commaunde<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> moreouer as it appereth in th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb facs="tcp:173926:14"/> epyſtel that he wrote to Arſacium byſhoppe of the Galatyans, that all his preſtes, which had turned wyth him fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> Chryſt, &amp; ſerued to gentilite: ſhuld folow the chriſtian religio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> in all poyntꝭ reſemble their lyues and co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>uerſation. Wyll you ſe what moued the deuyl to worke here his olde practyſe? wyll you ſe what made him to ſarch, for con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>corde and vnytye betwene the chri<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſtian preſtis and his? Doutles no thinge elſe but this, as the hyſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rye ſheweth: Iulianus ſeynge the feruour &amp; good lyfe of the chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an preſtis to be had in hye eſtima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>: wel knowing y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> the people cold not be ſeduced, as longe as they vſyd ſuche godlynes, and he ſuch naughtyneſſe: ferynge alſo leſte that their vertu ſhuld deſtroy his vyce, fell to agremente wyth the Chriſtyan preſtes: wyllynge his,
<pb facs="tcp:173926:15"/> gentylytye to folow in al poynte<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> the Chriſtian ſorte, that he mygh<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> the ſowner by this agreme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t brin<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> al to naught. But what nede v<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> to ſarche y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſcriptures for exa<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ple<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> in this craftye poynt of the deuyl what nede we turne y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> olde facte<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> of our fathers? ſeyng y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> the deuyl doth not ceaſſe in ower tyme, b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> doth admyniſter matter and exe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ples dayly tomoch in this behalf to vs. How he maketh enemyes t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> agree, and ſendeth the pharyſeis the Herodians to take Chriſt an<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> his myniſters in theyr wordes. The worlde (the more is the pity is full of ſchyſmes, full of diuerſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>te &amp; co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tentio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>: So<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>me goyng to f<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> on the one hande: ſomme to far<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> on the other. To fewe (if it pleaſe god) that kepe y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> kynges hye wa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> and walke in the myddell path Suche perſones when they co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb facs="tcp:173926:15"/> or ſende to heare a ſermo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mune reaſonynge, ye oftentymes fami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lier communication: they can not be content to comme alone, or ſend theyr faythfull ſeruaunt but they muſt brynge or ſend theyr phary<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeis and theyr Herodians. The phariſey, by interpretation, is he y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> is ſequeſted and diuyded from o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther: and by him I vnderſtande <hi>Singularite.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Luc. 13.</note> The Herodian after Chriſtes owne wordes is he, that hathe the foxes crafte: and by him I meane <hi>Subtelte:</hi> Two ſhrode companions <hi>ſyngularyte</hi> and <hi>ſub<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>telte.</hi> Now when men be to much addicted to their owne fantazyes: whan they be ons maryed to their one Imagination: what ſoeuer be preached, ſayd, or redde, contrarye to their opinion, theyr minde, their vicious behauour and lyfe: The phariſe and ſingularite can not
<pb facs="tcp:173926:16"/> abide it, naught it is in their ſigh ſingularytey reiecteth it, condem<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>neth it: and takyng y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Herodian ſubtelte with the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, ſearch al corners turne al wayes that can be to tro<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ble the trewth, and to kepe it vn<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>derneth the fote. The tyme hat<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> ben, whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> that thoſe whych haue o<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>cupyed this place, haue laboure<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> &amp; endeuoured them ſelues with a the grace geuyn to them to hau<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> pacifyed and haue ſette at quye<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> the weake and feble conſcyences of their audyens. And nowe (th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> more it is to be lamented) <hi>ſingular<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tye</hi> ſo ruleth: that he that can be<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> diſpute and reaſon a new matter in the pulpyt, he is the beſte prea<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>cher. <hi>Simplicitye</hi> than dyd edyfy<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> and made peace: <hi>Singularitye</hi> no<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> doth deſtroy and ſetteth men at <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ryaunce. Then was preachyng ſwete melodye, whan the pyp<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb facs="tcp:173926:16"/> were in tune: Nowe it is an vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwete noyſe: for the pipes yarryth. Then men endeuered them ſelues to fulfyl that in lyfe, which y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> other preached, herde or redde by worde. Now al our ſtudy is to here new &amp; ſtraunge thynges to ſpeke and ſet them forth galantly, and lytel or nothynge to do. whervppon it fo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loweth as the holy man ſaynt Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>da ſayth:<note place="margin">In epi. Ia<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>cobi, cap <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>3</note> 
               <hi>Qui ad predicandum ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bum <expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abquam"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>quam</ex>
                  </expan> ad faciendum procliuior eſt: plerun<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> per amorem iactantiae per ſtudium contentionis, per eloquentiae facilitatem, per inuidentiam aliorum docentium, per ignorantiam catholi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cae veritatis, ſtulticiae reatum incurrit.</hi> He that is more redier to preache, to reaſon, or to heare the worde of god, than to perfourme it in his li<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>uynge: oftentymes for the loue y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> he hath in boſtinge and ſettynge him ſelfe furth, for the deſyer that
<pb facs="tcp:173926:17"/> he hath in ſtrife and co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tention, b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> the redines and facilitye of elo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>quens, by enuy that he barethe <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> other teachers, and by ignoran<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> of the catholyke trewth, falleth <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> to extreme folyſhnes. The ſympl<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> men than bare away all the good<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nes: and nowe <hi>Singularitie</hi> wold<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> ſeme to haue al the lernynge wh<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>fore it is to be fered, that ſymplic<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tye hath violently plucked hea<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> to her, &amp; hath lefte to ſingularity greuous damnation: whiche kno<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>weth y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> lawe &amp; wyl of god, paſſet<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> all together in knowledge, and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>thinge in doynge. It is written o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> ſaynt Auguſtyne: that whan h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> had red the lyfe of a ſimple, plain<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> &amp; holy man, called Paulus, how vertuouſly he led his lyfe, and ye<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> beinge a man of no lernyng, wit<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> wepynge and ſyghynge teares ſayd thus, <hi>Surgunt indocti et rapi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb facs="tcp:173926:17"/> coelum, nos autem cum litteris noſtris mergimur in infernu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>:</hi> The poore vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lexned and ſimple people ryſith &amp; plucketh heauen to them, and we connynge men with all our lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nynge be drowned in hel. Beware of the phariſey. Avoyde <hi>Syngulari<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>te:</hi> Be gladde to heare the trueth of whoſe mouth ſo euer it comme. So let vs heare gods worde, that we may be the better for it, and ex<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>preſſe it in our lyfe. Awaye with the Herodian: farewell ſubteltye, and crafty circumuention: for ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rely ſaith Chriſt: Except ye turne,<note place="margin">Math. 18.</note> and become as chyldren, ye ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> not entre in to the kyngdom of heaue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. <hi>Singularyte</hi> &amp; <hi>Subtelte</hi> be make bates, they breke the peace and v<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nyte y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> ought be amonge chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans, they haue therfore no parte with chriſte.<note place="margin">Iaco. 3.</note> Saint Iames ſayeth If you haue bytter enuyenge and
<pb facs="tcp:173926:18"/> ſtryfe in your hartes, reioyce not, neyther be you lyers agayne the treuth. This wyſedome deſce<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>deth not fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> aboue: but is erthly, beaſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, &amp; deuellyſh: for where enuyeng &amp; ſtryfe is, there is vnſtablenes &amp; all maner of euyl workes. Playn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe &amp; ſymplycyte dryue euer to a concord, &amp; wold haue all me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to be one. They ſhal therfore enherite y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> earth of lyfe. They be the chyldre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of god: for ſo ſayth our ſauyoure Chriſt.<note place="margin">Math. 5.</note> 
               <hi>Beati pacifici quoniam ipſi fi lii dei vocabu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tur.</hi> Bleſſed be y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> peace makers, for they ſhalbe called the chyldren of god. To kepe this con<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>cord and vnite, euery man ſhuld applye his ſtudy. To this ſhulde we exercyſe our tounges. To this, ſhuld you geue your ears. Saint Ihon<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> euangelyſt (as ſaynt Hie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rome wryteth of hym) dwelling at Epheſus,<note place="margin">In co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>men. ſuper 6 ca<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>p<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. ad gala</note> &amp; beyng ſo olde, that he was not able to come abrode by
<pb facs="tcp:173926:18"/> hym ſelfe, wold be boren forthe in his diſcyples armes: &amp; co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mynge where as any multytude or co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nies of people was, thus wold he preache to them: <hi>Filioli, diligite alte rutrum.</hi> Dere ſonnes, loue you one an other. And co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>myng to another co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>pany wold preache y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſame &amp; no more. <hi>Filioli, diligite alterutru<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>.</hi> This co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tynuyng from daye to day both at home &amp; abrode, made his diſcy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples wery ſtyl to heare one thyng: whervpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> they aſked him: Why he preached none other thing but on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly this, <hi>Filioli diligite.</hi> And s. Ihon<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> geueth the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> an au<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſwer, mete for ſo holy a ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> as he was: <hi>Quia p<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ceptu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> dn<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>i eſt, et ſi ſolum fiat, ſufficit.</hi> I do preche this one thyng ſtyl to you, to loue one another: for it is gods co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>man<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>dement, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> ſo ye do: &amp; yf you ꝑforme this, it is ſufficie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t, ye nede none other thynge. In all good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe I pray god to make vs fren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dys
<pb facs="tcp:173926:19"/> and louers: that we all maye thinke and ſpeake one thinge and that there be no diſſention among vs:<note place="margin">1. Cor. 1.</note> but that we may be knyt toge<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ther in one mynde and in one mea<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nynge. In naughtynes ſtyll to be at varians, that we neuer conſent to it: nor come with the phariſeis and the Herodians vnder a cloke to take chriſt in his co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>municacio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. <hi>Magiſter ſcimus quia verax es, et via<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> dei in veritate doces, &amp; no<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> eſt tibi cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ra de aliquo: non enim reſpicis perſo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nam hominum.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>If an aungel had ben ſent from heauen to haue done a meſſage to chriſt: he coulde not haue hadde a better nor a more honorable in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duction or preface to his purpoſe, than was this, whiche the phary<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeis and Herodians here vſed to chriſt whan they ſayde: Mayſter, we knowe that thou art trew: and
<pb facs="tcp:173926:19"/> teacheſt y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> waye of god trewly: ney<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ther careſt y<hi rend="sup">u</hi> for any ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. Thou co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſidereſt not the perſon or eſtate of ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>.<note place="margin">Ioan. 13.</note> Thapoſtels called him may<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter, &amp; Chriſte dyd well alowe that name. <hi>Vos vocatis me magiſtrum &amp; dominu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> &amp; bene dicitis, ſum etenim.</hi> Yowe call me mayſter and lorde, and you ſay wel, for ſo I am. They prayſed him for the puryte of his lyfe, we knowe that thou art trew and lyueſt without ſpotte. They prayſed his lernynge to be blame<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe, thou teacheſt the way of god trewly. And laſt of al they prayſed him for keping of iuſtice: thou ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſt not for any man, for y<hi rend="sup">u</hi> art not parcyal to the ryche man, and iniu<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>rius to the pooer: But whether the perſon be ryche, whether he be pooer, of hye degre or lowe, frende or fo, there geueſte thou ſentence where the ryght wayth. The deuil
<pb facs="tcp:173926:20"/> oftentymes &amp; naughty men, may, and doth prophecy, and telleth the treuth: But it is done other igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rauntly or for an yll purpoſe.<note place="margin">Mat. 8.</note> The ii. deuils that poſſeſſed the .ii. mad men in the cou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>trey of Gergeſytꝭ, confeſſed Chryſt to be the ſonne of god: not for any loue or honour y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> they owed to chriſte, but onely for feare: for they ſore dowted leſte the tyme were come that they ſhuld be more greuouſly ponyſhed, &amp; loſe y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> poſſeſſions y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> they had in the crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turs of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> erth.<note place="margin">Ioan. 11.</note> Cayphas, nothing ente<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ding neyther y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> helth of mans ſoule, neyther y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> glory of chriſt: but only the ſauegarde of the te<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>porall kingdom of the Iues, prophecied &amp; ſaid treuth. It is better for vs y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> rather one man ſhulde dye for the people, than y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> all the people ſhuld periſh. Scripture ſayth, <hi>Hoc aute<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> a ſemetipſo no<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. dixit, ſed cu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, eſſet pon<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tifex anni illius, prophetauit, quod Ie<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſus
<pb facs="tcp:173926:20"/> moriturus erat pro gente.</hi> This ſpake he not of hym ſelfe: but be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ynge hye preeſt that ſame yere, he prophecyed that Ieſus ſhuld dye for the people. So in this our caſe the phariſees with the herodians be prophetes in theyr ſalutatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to chriſt: but they entended no ſuche thyng. They ſpake feare &amp; truely, but thought malycyouſly &amp; falſly. Lyke bees they came about chriſt bering outwardly in theyr mouth hony: &amp; inwardly in theyr hertes a ſharpe ſtynge. <hi>Haec eſt</hi> (ſaith Chry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoſtome) <hi>prima ſimulatio hypocrita<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ru<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, quia laudunt quos perdere volu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t.</hi> This is the fyrſt and chiefe poynt of an hypocrite &amp; dyſſembler, to prayſe them, whom they do vtter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly entende to deſtroye.</p>
            <p>Ioab pretended great frendſhyp towarde Abner,<note place="margin">2. Reg. 3.</note> when he ſende for hym as one frende ſhulde do for
<pb facs="tcp:173926:21"/> an other <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>o commune and talke <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> him, for his and the hole realme<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> profytte, but whan they came in <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> ſecrete place together,<note place="margin">2. Reg. 20,</note> Ioab dre<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> out his dagger and ſlewe Abne<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> The ſame Ioab, feryng, leſte Am<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſa ſhulde be preferryd in offyce b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>fore him with kynge Dauyd: wh<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> he knewe that Amaſa was com<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>mynge towarde the courte, diſſe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>blinge his malice, came to met<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> hym, &amp; with this fayre ſalutatio<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> greted hym. <hi>Salue frater Amaſa:</hi> al<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>hayle brother Amaſa, holdyng<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> hym by the chynne with the rygh<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> hande as thoughe he wolde hau<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> kyſſed hym: and preuely with his lyfte hand panched hym with hi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> dagger.<note place="margin">2. Reg. 13.</note> Abſolon pretendyd great loue towarde his father and his brothers, when he made his ſhere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhyp feaſt, and whan he colde no<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> obtayne his father to come to his feaſte
<pb facs="tcp:173926:21"/> he wolde haue no naye, but that Amnon with the reſydewe of his brothers ſhulde come: he ſayd, els his feaſt ſhulde be nothyng play<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſant. And whan they were moſte meryeſt, then was Amnon by Ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolons commaundement ſlayne.</p>
            <p>The traytor Iudas made a fayre face when he came to betraye his mayſter,<note place="margin">Mat. 2<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> with this flateryng ſalu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> and deadly kyſſe, <hi>Aue Rabbi:</hi> All hayle maiſter. But he lefte his ſtynge behynde with the Iues, when he ſayd: <hi>Quemcu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> oſculatus fuero, ipſe eſt, tenete eum.</hi> whome ſo euer I kyſſe, that is he, laye han<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>des vpon hym. More fayrer wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>des than is vſed now adayes was neuer heard: to promiſe much, and to performe lytell: to beare a fayre face outward, and deadly malyce inwarde. In one hande to haue fyer, and in the other water: To
<pb facs="tcp:173926:22" rendition="simple:additions"/> ſay as you ſaye: To holde vp ye &amp; naye, whether it be trewe, whether it be falſe: is counted mych cruyli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>te. To tell the treuth: to ſpeake as a man doth thynke: to contrarye the falſyte, &amp; to be playne in maſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters, is taken as lacke of good maners &amp; rude ruſticite. So mych is this flattery, this diſſimulatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> vſed amonge men: that excepte a man can flatter, excepte he can diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſemble, he is not mete to dwell a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monge men. The poete Inuenal, in reproche of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Romaynes vſyng this faute,<note place="margin">Satyr. 3</note> was not aferde to ſay: <hi>Quid Romae facia<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>? me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tiri neſcio: libru<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſi malus eſt ne queo laudare &amp; poſcent</hi> what ſhall I do at Rome? I can not ly: I can not diſſemble and flatter: I can not ſaye the croe is whyte, the ſwanne is black: I can not prayſe that boke to be good, whiche is naughte: I can not de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſyre
<pb facs="tcp:173926:22"/> that thynge to be ſette furth, whiche I knowe more meter to be ſuppreſſed. This and ſuche other thynges folowynge, lyke as the Hethen poete then ſpake agaynſt the Romaynes: ſo I doubte not: but yf he ſawe our lyues, he wolde ſaye the ſame, and myche more to our confuſion. Such hypocrites, ſuche dyſſemblers, ſuch flatterers be of all men moſte to be deteſted, moſte to be abhorred: for when they ſeme moſt to be with vs: then be they moſte agaynſte vs: when they pretende moſte frendſhyppe, then ought we moſt to feare theyr hatred. The common prouerbe dothe well declare what they be: <hi>Crocodili lachrimae:</hi> The teares and wepynge of the Crocodyle. The Crocodyle is myche deſirous of ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s fleſh: but yet before he wyl de<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>uowre any ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> he bitterly wepeth.
<pb facs="tcp:173926:23"/> The hypocryte &amp; flatterer in his herte deſyreth nothynge ſo mych, as his owne wordly aduantage: he careth not to what miſfortune his frende be dreuen to, ſo that he maye haue profytte of it: yet to beare a fayre face outwardly, he wepeth in the ſyght of the people, when in herte he is moſt gladdeſt. Of thoſe ſorte of men writeth the wyſe man in this maner.<note place="margin">Eccleſi. 12,</note> 
               <hi>In labiis ſuis indulcat inimicus, &amp; in corde ſuo inſidiatur, vt ſubuertat te in fouea<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. &amp;c</hi> Thy ennemy the flatterer and hy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pocrite in his lyppes beareth ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny, and ſpeaketh fayre: but in his herte he craftely layeth wyles, to hurle the into the dyche. Before thy eyes he wyll wepe, but whan he may eſpye a tyme, he wyll ſucke thy blod. If aduerſite happen to the, he wyll be one of the fyrſt that ſhall be agaynſt the, helpyng with
<pb facs="tcp:173926:23"/> all the ſtrengthe he can, to ouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>throwe the.<note place="margin">Super ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ti. cantico ſerm. 33.</note> The holy man ſaynt Bernard thynketh them not wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy the name of man, but calleth them, <hi>putridam tabem hominum,</hi> the rotten corruptio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of men: and thus he declareth theyr conditions.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Omnes amici &amp; omnes inimici: omnes neceſſarii, &amp; omnes aduerſarii: omnes domeſtici, &amp; nulli pacifici: oe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s proxi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mi, &amp; omnes quae ſua ſunt quaerunt: Miniſtri Chriſti ſunt &amp; ſeruiunt anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chriſto.</hi> All the ſorte of flaterers, wolde ſeme to be our frendes, but they be all enmyes: all they wolde be taken of the knotte of amytie, but they be of the knotte of emny<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie: all wolde be counted houſhold geſtes, but none of them ſtudyeth to make peace: all be our neygh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bours, but euery man is for hym<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſelfe, and ſeketh his owne co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dite and profite. They wolde be
<pb facs="tcp:173926:24"/> called Chryſtes mynyſters, but they ſerue the deuyll &amp; antichriſt. Beware of ſuch ſaith the wyſema<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>:<note place="margin">Pro. 1.</note> 
               <hi>Fili mi ſi te lactauerint peccatores, ne acquieſcas eis:</hi> My ſonne yf ſuche ſynners go about to fede the, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſente not to them. And god by his prophete Eſay.<note place="margin">Eſay. 3.</note> 
               <hi>Popule meus qui te beatum dicunt ipſi te decipiunt, &amp; via<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> greſſuum tuorum diſſipant.</hi> My peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple they that flattereth with the, and ſayth that thou arte bleſſed, they dyſceueth the, and bryngeth the out of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ryght way. And wher ſhal we ley the faute of the mayn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenaunce of this vyce? Surely in thoſe that dothe reioyſe to be flat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tered with all. It is true that one ſayeth. <hi>Si tu vis eſſe Thraſo nus<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abquam"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>quam</ex>
                  </expan> de<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> rit gnato:</hi> If thou delite to be flat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tered with all, thou ſhalte neuer myſſe flatterers: men be ſo blyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded nowe a dayes and ſo mych<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb facs="tcp:173926:24"/> ſtandeth in their owne conceite, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> the prouerbe whiche ſaynt Augu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtyne doth vſe is verified in vs.<note place="margin">Epiſt. 47, ad Procli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nianum.</note>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Creuit caput &amp; impinguatu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> eſt oleo.</hi> Our heades be growen great and fatted with oyle. I pray you, who is not glad nowe a days, ye in ma<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ner doth chale<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ge to him to be cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led, moſt holyeſt father: moſt mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cyfull and ryghtuous iudge.</p>
            <p>Good and louynge mayſter, fayth<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>full and wyſe ſeruaunt: diſcrete &amp; lerned preſt: true &amp; obedient ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iecte: with ſuch other names of of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fyces and dignityes: To thoſe we do applaude outwardly towarde the worlde: and inwardlye oure conſcience condemneth vs for it: and knoweth nothynge leſſe in vs than that. As for punyſhe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mente to them that delytethe in receyuynge ſuche vayne prayſe: I wolde deſyre none other (and
<pb facs="tcp:173926:25"/> that only te<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>porally, for ſauegarde of theyr ſoules) than happened to the great Alexander in ſuch a lyke matter.<note place="margin">Seneca e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſto. 70.</note> Flatterers had perſwaded Alexander that he was no mortal man: but was a god, &amp; that none of the lower ſorte, but Iupiters owne ſonne: the hyeſt god of all. And in this folyſhe paradyſe, he longe contynued. But as he beſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged a certayne cytie, &amp; there was ſore wounded with an arrowe in the thygh, hauyng payne intolle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable, dayly more and more incre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſyng, deſpayryng of his lyfe: con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſed openly that he was before tyme ſhamefully mocked with all, ſayeng: <hi>Omnes iurant me eſſe filium Iouis, ſed vulnus hoc homine<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> me eſſe clamat.</hi> Euery man boldely affir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meth and ſwereth that I am Iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piters ſonne: but this wounde of myne ſheweth openly and cryeth
<pb facs="tcp:173926:25"/> that I am a mortall ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. Herodes ſyttyng in his throne,<note place="margin">Acti. 2</note> takynge a vayne glorie when the people flat<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tered hym, ſayeng: <hi>Dei voces &amp; non hominis,</hi> It is the voyce of god y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſpeaketh, and not of man: was im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mediately ſmytten of the aungell of god, bycauſe he gaue not god the honour, and eaten with wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mes, or with the lowſy euyll, dyed. Let vs folowe ſaynt paules cou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſel, <hi>Gloria noſtra haec ſit,</hi>
               <note place="margin">2. Cor. 1.</note> 
               <hi>teſtimonium conſcientiae noſtrae.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Mat. 25.</note> Let vs reioyſe &amp; glorye in the teſtymony and clere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of our conſcyence. Let vs do as the fyue wyſe virgins dyd, car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rye oyle with vs: let vs not bye it of the ſellers: that is (after ſaynte Auſtyne.) <hi>ab adulatoribus,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Epiſt. 120 ad Hono<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ratum.</note> of flat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terers. <hi>Adulatores na<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> laudem ſuam tan<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abquam"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>quam</ex>
                  </expan> oleum venditant ſtultis.</hi> For flat terers do ſclle theyr prayſe, as it were oyle vnto fooles. Now af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter
<pb facs="tcp:173926:26"/> this flatteryng p<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>face, they pro<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>poſeth this queſtyon, and openeth theyr mindes. <hi>Dic nobis, quid tibi vi<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>detur, licet ce<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> dari Caeſari an non?</hi> Tel vs what thinkeſt y<hi rend="sup">u</hi> ought we or is it lawfull for vs to paye tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bute to Ceſer, or not? Here at le<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>gth is y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> chycke hatched, But one leyth y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> egge, &amp; an other ſitteth vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> it, &amp; bringeth forth y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> chycke.<note place="margin">Hiere. 17.</note> So it co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meth to paſſe, as y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ꝓphet Hieremy ſaith: <hi>Perdix fouit quae no<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> peperit.</hi> The partryge hath ſitten vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the egges,<note place="margin">Lib. 6. ca. 3</note> which ſhe neuer layde. S. Ambroſe in his Hexamero<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s. One partryge (ſaithe he) ſteleth an o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers egges: &amp; ſhe that ſteleth the egges ſitteth vpon the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> &amp; bringeth yongeons: But ſhe can haue no profytte of her thefte: for as ſowne as y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> yonge hereth the call and cry of her, which layd the egges: they forſaketh the nourſſhe and folo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>weth
<pb facs="tcp:173926:26"/> the true mother. The olde phariſees and chefe preſtis layde this egge. They ware the true mo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ther of this captious queſtio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to be moued: but the yonger ſort which ware as craftye as their mayſters ſet it forth: but they had lytel pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fytte of theyr broude, theyr labour came to no profe. <hi>Cognita aute<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> Ieſꝰ nequitia eoru<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, ait, Quid me te<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tatis hy<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>pocritae?</hi> For whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> Ieſꝰ ꝑceiued their malyce &amp; wyckednes, he ſayd, why do you te<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>pte me you hypocrites? Salomo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſaith truly:<note place="margin">prouer, 11.</note> 
               <hi>Iuſticia recto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ru<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> liberabit eos, &amp; i<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> inſidijs ſuis <abbr>capie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t</abbr> iniqui:</hi> Rightuouſnes ſhall diliuer good me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, &amp; craft at length ſhal de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceue his maiſter. Ieſus ſtreight w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> perceued their naughtynes, &amp; ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cordyng to y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> he ſayd, why do you te<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>pt me you hypocrytꝭ? They dyſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſemblyngly called hym mayſter: they flatteringely prayſed him for
<pb facs="tcp:173926:27"/> his vpryght lyfe, trewe doctryne, and good iuſtyce. And Chriſt with out flatterynge calleth them Hy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pocrites, diſſemblers, accordynge to theyr deſeruyng. They dyſſem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bled with Chriſtes goodnes: And Chriſte is playne w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> theyr naugh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tynes. In that geuyng vs a good leſſon, neuer to flatter with vice, but ſharpely to rebuke it: neuer to wynke there, where as we oughte to haue our eyes moſt open. This taughte vs before ſaynte Ihon<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the baptiſt,<note place="margin">Matthe. 3.</note> when he ſharpely re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proued the diſſimulation of the Phariſees and Saducees com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>myng faynyngly to be baptyſed of hym, ſayd: <hi>Progenies viparu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>: quis demonſtrauit vobis fugere a ventura ira?</hi> you adders kynde and genera<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, who cauſed you to fle from the vengean<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce to come.<note place="margin">Luc. 13.</note> This taught vs Chriſt whan he called Herode a fox. <hi>Ite, &amp; dicite vulpi illi.</hi> Go
<pb facs="tcp:173926:27"/> tell that fox.<note place="margin">Acto. 23.</note> This taught vs s. Paule, whan the hye preeſt Ana<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nias co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>maunded them that ſtode by Paule, to ſmyte hym on the mouth. He ſharpely aunſwered: God ſmyte the thou paynted wal, ſytteſt thou and iudgeſt me after the lawe, and co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>maundeſt me to be ſmytten contrary to the lawe?</p>
            <p>In vſynge ſuche ſharpe wordes, we be nothyng preiudiciall to the lenite of the goſpell:<note place="margin">Mat. 5.</note> where Chriſt ſayth, I ſay vnto you, who ſo euer is angry with his brother: ſhalbe in daunger of iudgement: who ſo euer ſaythe to his brother Racha, ſhalbe in daunger of a counſell: And who ſo euer calleth his bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther foole, ſhall be in daunger of hell fyre. For all this is to be vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtande (after Chriſoſtome) not to be done raſhely, without adui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſement, and without a ſufficient
<pb facs="tcp:173926:28"/> cauſe. A ſufficie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t cauſe is (as ſaint Auguſtin writeth) when a man is angry not with y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> perſon but with the offence.<note place="margin">Libro. 1. re<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tract. ca. 9,</note> 
               <hi>No<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> enim fratri iraſcitur, qui peccato fratris iraſcitur, qui ergo non peccato fratris iraſcitur, ſine cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſa iraſcitur.</hi> He is not angry with his brother, whiche is angry with his brothers offence: for he that is angry with any other thyng, than with the offence, he is angry with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out a cauſe. Thus dyd Chriſt here call them Hypocrytes, with y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> zele and deſyre to haue iuſtice kepte, and the treuth to be knowen, and not for any malyce or affecte to be reuenged vpon them.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Oſtendite mihi numiſma Cenſus. Cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ius eſt haec imago &amp; ſuperſcriptio.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Let me ſe the tribute mony. whoſe coyne, whoſe Image, &amp; ſuperſcrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion hath it? As the great clarke &amp; holy martyr Ignatins writeth to
<pb facs="tcp:173926:28"/> the Magneſions: <hi>Duos characteres in hominibus inuenimus: vnum quide<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> verae monete ſignaculum: alterum vero adulterinum. Pius enim homo &amp; reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gioſus vera moneta eſt, quae a deo for mata vel expreſſa eſt. Impius vero &amp; irreligioſus, falſa moneta eſt, noxia, adulterina, praua, quae non a deo ſed a diabolo facta eſt.</hi> Two pryntes, or two coynes we fynde amonge me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>: The one is the ſtampe of trewe money: and the other is a counter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feyted or forged coyne. Euery good man, and that feareth to fall into goddes daunger is trew mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ney, &amp; hath goddes ſtampe, god<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>des Image in hym. The wicked and vicious perſon, and he that careth nother for god nor for ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, is coper money, naught, and hath the deuyls prynte vpon it. There be ſo many kindes of vice rayning amonge vs, and ſo lyttell vertue,
<pb facs="tcp:173926:29"/> that it is to be fered, leſte y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> deuyll hath marked the greatter parte to hym, &amp; putteth Chriſt to the ſma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ler. One or .ii. coynes I wyl toche, and ſo paſſe ouer this matter. A coyne there is myche to be lamen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, and that amonge men that be of great rycheſſe: that is this: they haue to mych charite among the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>: they dryue all thynges to nye to the fyrſt creation. For as the boke of Geneſis dothe teache vs:<note place="margin">Geneſis, 1</note> god made at the fyrſte begynnyng all lyuely creatures mates together, the male and the female in euery kynde: but man he made fyrſt alo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne without a mate. And of this one all other came: to ſygnify, af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter the doctors myndes, that we ought to endeuer our ſelues to an<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>vnite. Men dryue (I ſay) to nye t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> this vnite: they can not abyde di<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>uyſion. For let there be a terme, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tenentrey,
<pb facs="tcp:173926:29"/> a ſmall cotage, or any o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther thynge, wherby any profytte maye comme: charyte ſo prycketh them, they muſt brynge it to one: come together it muſt: all muſt be oures: it lyeth commodyouſly for them, they be in loue w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> it: departe it ſhall not from them. Further<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>more, bycauſe it is coſtely to kepe many houſholdꝭ, they haue found a good prouiſion for y<hi rend="sup">e</hi>, one houſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hold ſhall ſerue for all. The poore men that before kepte honeſt and charytable houſes vpon it, muſte ſeke farder: they be not worthy to dwell ſo nye to men of worſhyp.</p>
            <p>Wold to god they wold loke ſom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>what lower, and not to clymme ſo hye to the fyrſte begynnyng of the worlde. Let them come downe to Abrahams &amp; Lothes tyme.<note place="margin">Gene. 1<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> Abra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ham and Loth hadde ſuch greate poſſeſſyo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s in ſhepe and other cat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tell,
<pb facs="tcp:173926:30"/> that the paſtures about was not able to fynd them bothe: wher vpon amonge theyr ſhephardes and other herde men, roſe greate ſtryfe &amp; debate. What dyd Abraa<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> in this matter? toke he all to hym ſelfe? Bad he Loth to ſeke abrode where he wolde? He was of power greate ynough to haue done ſo? no no. But content that his bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ſhulde haue a lyuyng as well as he: ye (and that is more to be marueyled at) contente to leue his owne to Loth, ſayd: I beſeche the brother Loth, let there be no chy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dynge betwene the and me, and be<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>twene my ſhephardes and thyne, for we be brothers. If thou wylte take on the lyfte hande, I wyll ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ke on the ryghte hande. If you take the ryght hande, I wyll take the lyfte hande. Now to enpoue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ryſhement of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> hoole realme, fewe
<pb facs="tcp:173926:30"/> take all. Houſeholdes be broken vp, and poore men go a beggyng. <hi>Cuius imago eſt haec?</hi> whoſe Image whoſe coyne is this? If it were goddes Image,<note place="margin">Eſai. 5.</note> y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> prophete Eſay wolde neuer haue ſayd by goddes mouth: <hi>Ve qui coniungitis domu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ad domum, &amp; agrum agro copulatis vſ<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> ad terminum loci: nunquid habitabi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tis vos ſoli in medio terrae?</hi> Wo to you that ioyne houſe to houſe, and couple fylde to fylde, paſture to paſture, that the poore can get no grounde amonge them, ſhall you dwell alone in the myddle of the earth? In tyme paſte were actes made agaynſt decayenge of hou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes, &amp; dwellynge places, and for a tyme was well obſerued &amp; kepte: and now a dayes many for feare of the ſtatute kepe vp the houſes: but as for the houſe holdyng they maynteyne ſo, that nother mowſe
<pb facs="tcp:173926:31"/> nor ſparowe wyll abyde there. Ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes alſo &amp; ſtatutes hath ben made to ſtynt men fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> great engroſſyng of fermes, and a certayne number of ſhepe to be kepte, and no man to paſſe that: but the lawes be of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tentymes as the philoſopher Ana<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>charſis was wont to ſay: <hi>Leges a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ranearum telis ſunt ſimiles, in quibus infirmio ra animalia haerent, valentio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ra autem perru<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>punt.</hi> Lawes be lyke to the cobbe webbe that the ſpy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders make, they holde faſte lytell flees and ſuche ſmall beaſtes: but the greater beaſtes breake thorow them, &amp; be not letted. To ſpeake of the coyne of horedome and ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uoutery was neuer ſo much nede: for the vice was neuer ſo muche vſed. This was ſo deteſtable in s. Paules conſcience that he wolde not haue it ones named amonge vs.<note place="margin">Ephe. 6.</note> Let fornication (ſayth he) and
<pb facs="tcp:173926:31"/> all vnclenlynes be not ones na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med amonge you, as it beco<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>meth ſaintes. And we to haue the fylthy communication of it ſtyll in our mouthes, counte it mery bordyng. The ſynfull acte of it is wynked at. No man doth pownyſhe it, and therfore no man dothe feare it.</p>
            <p>Chriſt ſayth:<note place="margin">Mat. 5.</note> that who ſo euer lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth vpon a woman, luſtyng after her, he hath co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mytted aduoutery with her in his herte. And we be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leue that it is no ſynne to co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mytte actually the foule dede. We beleue not (I ſaye) that it is offence: for yf we dyd beleue, we wolde feare the ſharpe iudgeme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t of god, whi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>che he threateneth vpon this vice, and ſo wolde forbeare it.<note place="margin">Serm. 243 <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e tempo.</note> Saynte Auguſtyn ſayth, <hi>Si enim fidem ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berent, vti<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> deo crederent, &amp; venturu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> iudiciu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> cum tremore metuerent: pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>batur enim quia hominibus credunt,
<pb facs="tcp:173926:32"/> &amp; deo non credunt, vt publice vbi ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mines vident, adulteria timeanr: &amp; ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crete vbi deus videt omnino non ti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meant. Si quale<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>cu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> ſcintilla<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> fidei ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berent, ſicut non permittunt ſeruos in praeſentia ſua peccare, ita nec illi in co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſpectu domini ſui adulterare praeſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merent.</hi> If we had fayth, trewly we wolde gyue credence to god, &amp; wolde tremblyngly feare god<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>des iudgeme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t. But now it is pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bable, and we may by preſumptio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſaye, that we beleue man and not god, bycauſe we feare to co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mytte aduowtery openly where ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> may ſe vs, and pryuely to do it where god may ſe vs, we feare nothynge at all. If there were any ſparkle of fayth in vs, lyke as we wolde not ſuffre our ſeruau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tes to offend in oure preſens: ſo lyke wyſe we wolde not preſume to offende in the ſyghte of our mayſter abou<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> whiche ſeeth as well in darkenes
<pb facs="tcp:173926:32"/> as in lyghte. But we be the fooles of whome the prophete ſpake. <hi>Dixit inſipiens in corde ſuo non eſt deus.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Pſal. 13.</note> The foole and the vnwyſe man ſayde in his harte that there was no god. For this is for a cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taynte, that he dothe not beleue god to be, whiche pryuely and in corners wyll do that thyng in the preſens of god, whiche openly in the preſens of man he is a fearde to do.<note place="margin">Gene. 12.</note> Pharao kynge of Egypte takynge Saray in to his houſe, knowyng none other but that ſhe was Abraams ſyſter, and not his wyfe, commyttynge no vnlawfull acte with her, was ſore ponyſhed for it. The texte ſayth: <hi>Flagellauit dominus pharaonem plagis maximis &amp; domum eius propter Sarai vxorem Abraae.</hi> God ſcurged Pharao gre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uouſly, and all his houſholde, by<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe
<pb facs="tcp:173926:33"/> of Saray Abraames wyfe. Abimelech lyke wyſe kyng of Ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rare,<note place="margin">Gene. 20.</note> beyng enformed of Abraam, that Saray was his ſyſter, and not his wyfe doynge no vyleny with her, but takyng her into his houſe, harde of goddes mouthe: <hi>En morieris propter mulierem quam tuliſti,</hi> Lo thou ſhalte dye, bycauſe thou haſte taken this woman to the. Ignorans here is ponyſſhed for taking of an other mans wyfe in to theyr houſes, without any le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cherous acte co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mytted? And ſhall we ſcape vnpunyſhed, vnlawful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly doynge the fowle acte? No no: god wyll not alowe this coyne: it is not his, <hi>ſignatum eſt,</hi> it is ſcaled vp for the deuyll. In the boke of Deuteronomy,<note place="margin">Cap. 28.</note> god ſhewed what coyne he wold haue, when he ſaid <hi>No<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> erit meritrix de filiabus iſrael, nec ſcortator de filiis iſrael.</hi> There ſhall
<pb facs="tcp:173926:33"/> be no harlette among the dough<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters of Iſraell: nor no hore hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter amonge the ſonnes of Iſraell. Whether this precept of god may ſtande or no, with y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> comon ſtues, I put it to your iudgement. This dare I ſaye, that it is a deteſtable prouocation for youth: here they may ſynne, &amp; no man ſay agaynſt them: Let the wyfe dyſpleaſe her houſebande: the doughter her fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther and mother, the ſeruaunt her mayſter &amp; dame, hyther they maye come without naye: here is a ſafe-conducte for them. Well it may be permytted by a cyuyle ordynance, goddes lawes, I am ſure dyd ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer permytte it. Sufferyd it maye be to auoyde worſe inco<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>uenience: but the meane tyme many be loſte bothe body and ſoule: where as yf ſuche impunite and liberte to ſyn were not, very feare and ſhame
<pb facs="tcp:173926:34"/> wolde haue prohibyte men, &amp; kept them honeſt. This and ſuch other lyke be the deuylles coyne: this is coper and naughty mony. Caſte we therfore of, this pryntes: it is the deuylles, to the deuyll than w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> it. Let vs ſuffre it no longer to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mayne amonge vs, leſte the deuyl chalenge vs for his, yf he fynde his marke vpon vs.</p>
            <p>When the pharyſees had ſhowed to Chryſte a peny of the trybute mony: and by theyr owne confeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſyon ſayde, that it was the empe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rours coyne, he ſayd: <hi>Reddite er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>go quae ſunt Caeſaris Caeſari, &amp; quae ſunt dei deo.</hi> Reſtore therfore and pay to Ceaſar that which is Cea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſars, &amp; gyue or yelde to god, that whiche is goddes. An euydente place and a manyfeſt authorite to proue that euery Chriſtyan man is bounde to obey the cyuyle ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gyſtrates
<pb facs="tcp:173926:34"/> and worldly offycers. And that god dothe alowe them, in that he geueth vs co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>maunde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment to paye them that is theyr duty: to obey and ſerue them in temporall bodely and outwardly goodes. Paye to Ceaſar, to kyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges, to the worldly rulers, that whiche is theyrs, and to god his duty.<note place="margin">In. 22. Mat.</note> To Ceaſar we oughte to paye (after ſaint Hieromes mynd) <hi>Nummu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, pecunia<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, tributum,</hi> Our ry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches, mony &amp; tribu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e: An example of this chriſt gaue vs in his owne ꝑſon, when he ſayd to Peter,<note place="margin">Mat. 17.</note> 
               <hi>Solue pro me &amp; te,</hi> Pay trybute for me &amp; for the.<note place="margin">Rom. 13</note> The powers be ordeyned of god, therfore we ought reuere<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to obey the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>: they be y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> miniſters of god for our welth: al their care &amp; ſtudy is how they maye delyuer vs fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> our enemyes, how to bryng vs out of captiuite and bondage.
<pb facs="tcp:173926:35"/> A lyuely Image of this may eue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry trewe ſubiecte ſe in oure moſte victorious prynce y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> kynges moſt excellent maieſte: what daunge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous iurneyes he taketh bothe by water and by lande, at home and turth, to ſet vs at reſte. what vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpeakeable coſtes he hath ben, &amp; is continually at, and all for oure quietnes and welthe. Rede all the Hyſtories that euer hath ben wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten or done, and in compariſon to his gracyous affayres, they ſhall be but ſhadowes. wherfore ſhewe we agayn to hym as we are bou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d to do, our obedyent hartes: ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mytte we our ſelues to hym, he is our ſupreme head vnder almygh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty god. Refuſe we the vſurped power of the byſhop of Rome: re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>membre we our othe made to the ſupremite of the kynges grace: let vs performe y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> in herte, &amp; thynke
<pb facs="tcp:173926:35"/> inwardly, as outwardly by mouth we haue ſworne. Thus let euery men ſhewe to hym his obeyſance. To this ſaint Paule doth exhorte vs, not onely for feare of venge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance, but bycauſe of conſcience. And ſtreyght wayes he inferreth: and for this cauſe paye you tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bute: helpe hym with ſuch as god hath lente you, for ſo be you bou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d in co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſcience. If we haue any thing to hym gyue we thankes, for by his trauayle &amp; labour he maketh vs quyet poſſeſſyoners. In his affayres therfore, whan he nedeth we ought to put our helping han<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>des. So ſayth the holy byſhoppe Hylariꝰ pictauienſis: <hi>Si nihil quod Caeſaris eſt penes nos teſederit, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditione reddend<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> ei quae ſua ſunt non tenebimur. Porro autem ſi tebus illius incu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>bamus, ſi iure poteſtatis ſuae vti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mur, extra querelam iniuriae eſt, redde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re
<pb facs="tcp:173926:36"/> Caeſari quod Caeſaris eſt.</hi> If we haue nothynge remayninge with vs, that is Ceaſars, tha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> be we not bound to paye hym that which is his. But yf we occupye his good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes, yf we vſe the ryght of his po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wer, and vnder that be defended, it is without any co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>playnt of in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iury, that we paye Ceaſar that whiche is Ceaſars. Forthermore yf we well ponder and conſyder this worde <hi>Reddite,</hi> Reſtore, yelde: we maye lyghtly parceyue, that this to do is not only gentylnes, but in this parte of dewty we are bounde ſo to do. And that very well doth Theophilact note com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentynge vppon the .xx. chapiter of Luke. <hi>Vide quia non dixit date, ſed reddite: debitum igitur inquit, eſt. Reddite igitur debitum. Cuſto dit te princeps tuus ab hoſtibus, vitam tua<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> pacatam facit, debes ita<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> ei pro iis
<pb facs="tcp:173926:36"/> tributum.</hi> Marke (ſayth Theophi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lacte) Chriſte ſayde not geue, but paye and reſtore, than it is dette: Reſtore therfore the dette. Thy prynce and kynge dothe kepe and defende the from thy enemyes: he cauſeth the to lyue at reſt, for thoſe thynges therfore, thou arte det<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tor to hym and bound to paye tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bute. He goeth forther and ſayth. <hi>Etiam ipſum quem habes nummum ab illo habes. Igitur cum nomiſma re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gis iterum illi reddis, interim tibi lu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>craris, quod per ipſum, quae vitae de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bita ſunt preſtantur.</hi> The mony alſo that thou haſte, thou haſte it of hym: Therfore whan thou reſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſt to the kynge agayne his mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nye: thou getteſt this luker to thy ſelfe, in that by it thou prepareſte ſuche thynges for the, as be neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſary to maynteyne thy lyfe.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:173926:37"/>
            <p>Be we than obedient in this par<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> and accordynge to Chriſtes com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maundement: let vs paye to Cea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſar that whiche is Ceaſars parte, <hi>Ft quae ſunt dei deo.</hi> And goddes part to god. After ſaynt Hierome. <hi>Decimas, primitias, oblationes, &amp; vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctimas.</hi> Teathes, the fyrſte <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>gather offerynges, and ſacrifice. In the olde lawe howe that the teathes were co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>maunded to be payed it is to manifeſte, one place therfore ſhal ſuffice.<note place="margin">Capi. 14.</note> In the Deuteronomy it is commaundyd: <hi>Decimam parte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſeparabis de cu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ctis fructibus tuis quae naſcuntur in terra per ſingulos annos,</hi> and by and by after, <hi>decima<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> frume<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> tui &amp; vini &amp; olei &amp; primo genita de a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> mentis &amp; ouibus tuis: vt diſcas timere dominum deum tuu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> in omni te<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>pore.</hi> Thou ſhalte ſeperate &amp; put apart the tethe of all the frute which the earth bryngeth forth to the euery yeare. The teth alſo of thy grayne
<pb facs="tcp:173926:37"/> and of thy wyne &amp; oyle: The fyrſte gendrynge of thy greatter beaſt, and of thy ſhepe that thou mayſte learne to feare thy lorde god at al tymes.<note place="margin">1. Cor. 9.</note> Saynte Paule at large doth proue, that in the euangeli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>call law, thoſe that dothe ſerue to the aulter, ſhulde lyue by the aul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter. Chryſt hym ſelfe although he reproued the ſiniſtrall iudgement of the ſcrybes &amp; phariſees, whiche prefarred the teathes of myntes, anys, and rewe before the waygh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tier maters of the lawe as iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, mercy and fayth. Yet he dyd not reproue ſuche teathes, but by his owne wordes bounde vs to paye them, ſayeng: <hi>Haec oportet fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cere &amp; illa non omittere.</hi> Specyally we be bounde to kepe iugement, mercy and fayth, &amp; yet be we bou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d alſo not to omytte &amp; leue vnpayd our teathes. Saynt Auguſtine in
<pb facs="tcp:173926:38"/> a boke that he intyteleth, <hi>De recti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tudine co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>uerſationis catholicae,</hi> thus writeth: <hi>Vnuſquiſ<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> de quali ingenio vel artificio viuit, de ipſo decima<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>net. Conſideret quia omnia dei ſunt per quae viuit, ſiue terra, ſiue flumina, ſiue ſemina, vel omnia quae ſub coelo ſunt vel ſuper coelos. Et ſi ipſe non de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diſſet, nihil vti<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> haberet, na<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> deus qui dignatur totu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> dare, decimam de ſuo dignatur nobis repetere, non ſibi pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitus ſed nobis profuturam.</hi> Euery man of what faculte or crafte ſo euer he be, of that let hym teathe, let hym co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſyder, that al is goddes wherby he lyueth, whether it be the earth, the water, ſedes, vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nethe heauen or aboue heauen, all is goddes. And except he had ſent it, we had had nothyng: God ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore whiche gaue vs all together, doth vouchſaue to aſke the teath of vs agayne, not for his but for our great profytte: and prouynge
<pb facs="tcp:173926:38"/> this by the teſtymony of the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phete Malachy, the thyrde chapi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, inferreth: <hi>Nolite de cuncta ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtantia veſtra fraudare decimam, ne vobis nouem partes auferantur &amp; ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>la decima remaneat.</hi> Defraude not your teathes of any parte of your ſubſtau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce, leſte that the nyne par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes be taken from you, and onely the tenth remayne with you. For as the ſame ſaynt Auguſtyn ſayth in a ſermon.<note place="margin">Serm. 219. de tempo.</note> 
               <hi>Haec eſt domini iuſtiſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ma conſuetudo, vt ſi illi decimam non dederis, tu ad decimam reuoceris.</hi> This is goddes moſt ryghtuous cuſtome, that yf thou paye not the tenth to hym, he wyll dryue the to the tenthe only. Let vs be obedie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t both to god &amp; to man, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> in bothe partes we be fou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d giltles, payeng to Ceaſar y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> which is Ceaſars, &amp; to god that which is goddes. Aboue al thinges let vs apply our ende<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uour
<pb facs="tcp:173926:39"/> to ſet forth the glory of god, to mayntayne the trewe catholike fayth of chriſte: and to vſe ſuche meanes as may moſt make to this ende. And what meanes is that? Surely the fact of Iulianus tea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cheth vs.<note place="margin">Augu. li. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>feſ. ca. 5.</note> Iulianus intendyng to deſtroy the fayth of Chriſte, com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maunded no learnynge nor ſcoles to be had among the chriſtians in his empyre, well knowynge that whan all learnyng were gone, the fayth wolde ſoone decaye after. Wherfore we maye gether of the contrary that the chiefeſt meanes to mayntayne the fayth is to ſette vp learnyng, to mayntayne ſcoles to put youre chyldren to knowe, what the wyll of god is, and ſo to be able afterwarde to teache other the ſame. It was neuer more nede to ſpeake and crye vpon it. The vniuerſitees decaye: Gra<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mer ſco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>les
<pb facs="tcp:173926:39"/> be deſolated. The olde trees by reaſon of age weare away and gdy: there is nother ſlyppes nor eraffes newe planted: it is to be feared therfore, that there wyll be no more orchardes: it is to be fea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red that the fayth wyl away. The kynges grace of his bountyfull goodnes, well co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſideryng this de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cay, hath gracyouſly erected i<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> eche vniuerſitees of this his realme .v. leſſons: the ſtypende aryſynge to foure hundreth pounde yerely: be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſyde his gracyous exhibitio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s ſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mountynge farre the ſumme be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore ſpoken of. This to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> maynte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naunce of chriſtes fayth and ſet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tynge furth of good learnyng, his grace hath done: folowe, folowe for the reuerence of god, folowe &amp; helpe furth good learnyng, the key of chriſtes fayth. Moche you haue of your owne, moche cometh
<pb facs="tcp:173926:40"/> dayely by exectorſſhyp, defraude not y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> dead, be trewe to them, helpe poore ſcolers, helpe poore widow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>es, helpe the poore pryſoners that lye in chaynes &amp; yrons. Set furth the glorye of god in this poynt: &amp; ſo ſhal you performe this his pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cepte, payeng to Ceaſar that whi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>che is Ceaſars, and to god, that whiche is goddes part. Play here the trewe ſtuerdes, &amp; god ſhall ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cepte your counte, admittyng you to be cyteſins of his gloryous and tryumphant cytie, where as your names ſhall be wryten in the boke of lyfe, to enioy the eternall kyng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome: which graunt vs the father the ſonne and the holy ghoſte: to whome be glory, honor, &amp; empyre, for euer. Amen:</p>
            <trailer>¶Here endeth mayſter Chedſey ſermon.</trailer>
         </div>
         <div type="sermon">
            <pb facs="tcp:173926:40"/>
            <head>¶Here begynneth mayſter Scottes Sermon.</head>
            <epigraph>
               <q>
                  <p>Miſerunt Iudaei ad Ioannem.</p>
                  <bibl>Iohn<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. 1.</bibl>
               </q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>HE Iewes ſente from Hieruſalem preſtes and Leui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes to Iohn<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, that they ſhulde aſke him what arte y<hi rend="sup">u</hi>? And he confeſſed, and dyd not de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny, and he dyd confeſſe, ſayeng. I am not chriſt. And they aſked him, what then art thou Elias? and he ſayde I am not, arte thou the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phete? and he aunſwered, no, they ſayde therfore vnto him, what arte thou? that we may giue an anſwer to them that ſent vs, he ſaide, I am the voyce of a cryer in wilderneſſe. Make ready the waye of our lord as Iſaie y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> prophet dyd ſay. Iho. 1.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:173926:41"/>
            <p>THe Iewes dyd knowe by the propheſie of Iacob the Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>triarke,<note place="margin">Gen. 4.9.</note> that they ſhulde al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wayes haue amongeſt them a ru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ler of their owne nacio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of the tribe and familie of Iudas vnto ſuche tyme as Meſſias ſhulde come to delyuer them out of captiuite and bondage. Wherfore they ſeynge their kyndome deuided into foure partes, and ruled of foure Alyens and ſtraungers appoynted by the Romaynes to haue rule and domi<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nion ouer them, dide thincke that Chriſt was at hande, which expec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation and hoope of his commyng (as Origen doth ſaye) dide great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly comfort them, in ſoo muche that certaine factions and buſie fello<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wes did take vppon them, and pre<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tended as they had ben chriſt draw<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ynge after them much people vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der a pretence of delyueringe the
<pb facs="tcp:173926:41"/> Iewes out of the bondage &amp; cap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiuite of the Romaynes as was Theudas and Iudas Galileus,<note place="margin">Act. 5.18. Ioſe. 1 20.4.</note> as it doth appere in thactes of the Apoſtels, and more at large in the Antiquites of Ioſephus, but they were ſhortly extinguiſhed and dy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroyed, not withſtandyng the Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wes contynuynge in their hope, &amp; expectation of the commynge of Chriſt: when they dydde ſe Iohn<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> Baptiſt appere in wylderneſſe, a ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> lyued after a ſtreyght &amp; hard faſhyo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, vſing none other delicates then the wilderneſſe dyd miniſter vnto him. Apareled in homely, and vnpleaſaunte clothinge, made of heare, preachinge earneſtlye vnto the people penaunce. Baptiſinge them in water as to prepare the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to Chriſte. And alſo (as Ioſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phus doth teſtifie) teaching them the vſe of baptiſme, they dyd come
<pb facs="tcp:173926:42"/> runnynge vnto him out of euerye place, and gaue ſuche credence to his preceptes that many of the peo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ple thought he had bene chriſte,<note place="margin">Luc. 3.</note> but that ye may more playnly per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiue both the preachinge of Iohn<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> and alſo the opinion of the people towardes him. I ſhall open vnto you the teſtimonie of Ioſephus he ſayth thus.<note place="margin">18. Anti. 10</note> 
               <hi>Iohannem (qui vocabitur Baptiſta) occidit Herodes.</hi> Herode ſlewe Iohn<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> that was called Bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſt a very good man, whiche dyd byd the Iewes y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> they ſhold apply vertue, exerciſe iuſtice, &amp; lyue well diſpoſedlye toward god. And that they ſhulde growe as it were into one body by Baptime, ſayeng that Baptime ſhold then be acceptable, if it were not only taken to waſſhe away ſynnes that be paſt, but yf it be alſo kept for chaſtitie of the bo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>dy, puritie of the ſoule, and be had
<pb facs="tcp:173926:42"/> as a ſure ſeale, or cloſet of all ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tues and when he taughte them thus, the people came runnyng to him on euery ſyde, and were ready to obey hym in all thinges, thus farre Ioſephus. Nowe at the ſame tyme alſo our ſauiour Chriſt beganne to be notable, bothe by his preachinge, and by wonders and miracles that he wroughte, whiche althoughe manye of the common people, dydde well eſteme and receyue, yet notwythſtandyng the Pharyſees Scrybes, and hygh preeſtes did grudge agaynſt them greatlye enuyenge, and mali<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſynge Chriſte, wherefore of the opynyon that the common peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple hadde conceyued of Iohn<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, and of the malyce and dyſdayne that the Pharyſees, Scrybes, and hyghe preeſtes had agaynſt
<pb facs="tcp:173926:43"/> Chriſt, they ſent vnto Iohn<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to aſke him if he were chriſt, for no fauour nor good mynde that they had to Iohn<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> but for the malice &amp; hatred that they bare towarde Chriſt, co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uetynge to haue the teſtimonie of Iohn<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> for a tyme agaynſt Chriſte, whoſe eſtimation, which they per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceyued dyd beginne to be great a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongeſt y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> people, they wold haue quenched, as Chriſt dooth witnes him ſelfe,<note place="margin">Ioh. 5.</note> ſayenge. <hi>Vos miſiſtis ad Ioannem.</hi> you ſent vnto Iohn<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, and he dyd witneſſe with me, he was a ſhynynge and a burnynge candle &amp; you wolde haue reioyſed in his lyght for a tyme. Nowe they dyd ſende of this meaſage not of the commyn ſorte as they dyd the 7 of Iohn<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to take Chriſt, but they ſent preiſtes and Leuites, that is to ſay men of mooſt Aucthorite with the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> and as they were thought of moſt
<pb facs="tcp:173926:43"/> wyſedome, and learnynge, ſuch as might with their Aucthorite moue him, and by flatterie perſwade him to ſaye that he were Chriſt. And here is iuſte occaſion miniſtred vn<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>to me, to ſpeake of the preſtes both of tholde law and of the newe, whi<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>che thinge I wyll do ſo briefly as I can. <hi>Preces.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Preeſtes in the olde lawe were al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wayes electe and choſen of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> tribe of Leui, and of the ſtocke of Aaron to ſtande longe in makinge reher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſall of the ceremonies that they v<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed it ſhulde be not onely for this matter ſuperfluouſe, but alſo vnto you veray tedious. Wherefore I wyll ſpeake no more of them then ſaint Paul dothe to the Hebrues, that is that they were as meanes, apointed betwene the people, and god, to offer vp vnto god ſacrifice and oblation ſoo well for theſyn<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>es
<pb facs="tcp:173926:44"/> and ignorances of them ſelfes, as of the people, which ſacrifices &amp; ob<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>lations, could in no co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>dition pury<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fye, nor make cleane the conſcience of the worſhypper, for they dyd co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſte in outward thinges,<note place="margin">Hebre. 9.</note> but chriſt comyng a biſſhop of good thinges by a more large &amp; a more perfaite tabernacle, not made with mans hand, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> is to ſay, not of this kynde of buyldyng, not by the bloode, of gootes &amp; calues, but by his owne precyouſe bloode, entred ones into the holy place, hauyng found euer laſtynge redemption: This is the preeſt that Dauyd dyd ſpeake on, which is of thorder of Melchiſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dech, this is y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> preeſt which offered vp thonly oblatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> whiche pacified the wrath of the father of heuen, &amp; reconciled agayne man vnto hym, ſtoppyng vp the deuels mouthe, &amp; payeng the ſu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>me dew for y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> forfait,
<pb facs="tcp:173926:44"/> &amp; tranſgreſſyo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> accordyng to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eng of Dauyd. <hi>Miſericordia,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Sſal. 84</note> 
               <hi>&amp; veri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tas obuiauerunt ſibi, iuſticia &amp; pax oſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culati ſuut.</hi> Mercy &amp; truth hath met together, &amp; iuſtice &amp; peace hath kyſ<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſed. This high preeſt chriſt taking away y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> preeſthoode of tholde lawe whiche was but a ſhadowe, and a fygure gyuen for a tyme: dyd con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtitute a new order of preſtes, whi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>che ſhold not be occupied in vayne &amp; outward thynges as the forther were: but y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> ſhuld offre vp to god y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> father in a ſauour of a ſwete ſmel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lyng, his bleſſed body &amp; bloud in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſacrame<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t of thaulter. which ſholde alſo miniſter the ſacrame<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tes of the churche, wherby (as by meanes) grace is gyuen of god by chriſt vn<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>to man, &amp; be dilige<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tly occupyed in declaryng his word to the people: whoſe lyfe, co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>uerſatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, &amp; behauour of what ſort it ſhold be ſaint Paul
<pb facs="tcp:173926:45"/> doth declare plainly in Timothe, ſayenge.<note place="margin">1. Tim. 4.</note> 
               <hi>Eſto forma fidelium.</hi> Looke that thou be an exa<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ple of the faith in worde and communication, in lief, and conuerſation in loue, in ſpirite, in faith in puritie, applie thy ſelfe to readyng, exhortynge &amp; teaching, and doctrine, do not ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>glect the gifte that is in the, which is giuen vnto the by prophecye, with impoſition or layeng handes vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the, by the authorite of prieſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hood, exerciſe theſe thinges and be all togeather in theſe thinges, that thy progreſſe, and goynge forwarde may be manifeſte, to all men,<note place="margin">Tit. 1.</note> lykewiſe vnto Tite he ſayth. <hi>Oportet Epiſcopum inculpatum eſſe,</hi> It is neceſſary for a Biſſhop or a preeſt to be blameles, as the ſte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>warde of god, not ſtubburne, not angrye, not a drunckerde, not a brawler, nor a fyghter, not fylthily
<pb facs="tcp:173926:45"/> gyuen to lucre, but a keper of ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpitalite, ſtudious of thinges that be good, ſobre rightuouſe, godly, temperate, cleuyng faſt vnto that faithfull worde that is accordyng to learnyng, that he be able to ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>horte &amp; teache by holſom lernyng, and to confute them that ſaye the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>trarie. Now how farre the lyfes of many preſtes haue ben, and yet be ſtyll, from this rule of ſaynte Paule, I ſpeake this agaynſt my wyll, beynge ſory for it. It is vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowen to no man in ſo moch that the hole order of preſthode, which was wonte to be had in great re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>putation, as the worthineſſe of the thyng doth requyre, is ſo ronne in contempte, that it is now nothing elles but a laughynge ſtocke for the people, and ſure that wold not be ſo:<note place="margin">1. Tim. 5.</note> for <hi>Qui bene preſunt preſbyte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ri, duplici honore digni habentur.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb facs="tcp:173926:46"/>
            <p>Thoſe preſtes that do rule &amp; loke to theyr cure well, be worthy dou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble honor. And yf that a man wold conſider ſeuerally euery condition and ſorte of men, he ſholde fynde no one ſtate, wherin there be not very many which nothynge do ly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ue accordynge to theyr vocation: &amp; yet when as this dothe come to paſſe in euery condition and ſorte of men, only y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> hole order of preſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hode, is therfore deſpiſed and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempned: yf that for the myſbeha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uour &amp; naughty lyfe of certayne, the hole co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>pany ſhold be deſpiſed: why then be not the apoſtles of Chriſte co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>temned, which were but twelue in nombre, and one of them was a deuell, and dyd betraye his maiſter. Amongeſt the diſciples of ſaint Paule Philetus and Hymi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neus dyd forſake theyr mayſter, and fell to hereſye.<note place="margin">2. Timo 2</note> Demas dyd
<pb facs="tcp:173926:46"/> forſake hym alſo, and gaue hym ſelfe to the pleaſures of the world. Alexander the blackſmith dyd not onely forſake hym,<note place="margin">2. Tim. 4.</note> but alſo beſy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>des he dydde hym greate diſplea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſures: yet notwithſtandynge, Ti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mothe, Tite, and Luke, with other mo, dyd continewe faithfull. And we doo not reade, that euer the naughtynes of theyr felowes was caſt vnto them, as for a rebuke. I do greatly meruayl, that ſeynge in theſe dayes men be ſo well ſene in ſcripture, that they can not ſpye amonges all other thinges, howe they ſhold vſe them ſelues towar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>des preſtes. Saint Paule ſayth. <hi>Rogamus vos fratres vt cognoſcatis eos qui laborant inter vos.</hi>
               <note place="margin">1. Theſ. 5.</note> we beſech you brethren, that ye wold knowe them whiche do labour amongeſt you, and haue the ouerſyghte of you in the lorde, and do admonyſh
<pb facs="tcp:173926:47"/> you that ye haue them in greate pryce or eſtimation by loue, for theyr workes ſake, and be at peace with them. Alſo to the Hebrues: <hi>Parete his qui praeſunt vobis &amp;c.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Hebre. 1<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.</note>
            </p>
            <p>Obey them that haue the ouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſyght of you, and ſubmitte your ſelues vnto them, for they watche for your ſoules euen as they that muſte gyue accompt therfore, that they do it with ioye, and not with grefe, for that is not profitable for you. Saynte Paule byddeth you that ye ſhold obey them, and you in all condicio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s do withſtand them: He byddeth that ye ſholde ſubiecte and ſubmitte your ſelues vnto them: &amp; you wyll haue them ſubiect vnto all other, and as they were abiectes and caſtawayes: you make exclamatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> after a moſt vngodly faſhyon agaynſte them: But peraduenture here ſome wyll
<pb facs="tcp:173926:47"/> ſaye vnto me that they be no bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter worthy for they be but fooles &amp; negligent in doing their deuties, but I ſaye vnto theſe againe, that they them ſelues be more fooles, which al together do omitte theyr owne deuties, and be ſo curyous in fyndynge faultes with other men, and thinke that is leafull for them, all together to forſloo theyr owne deuties, bycauſe that other be negligent in doynge of theyrs.<note place="margin">Math 7.</note> But vnto ſuch doth chriſt ſpeake, ſayenge: Thou foole, and blynde fellowe: fyrſt caſt the great blocke out of thyne owne eye, &amp; then thou ſhalt ſe to take a little mote out of thy fellowes eye, lykewyſe ſaynt Paule ſaith vnto the ſame.<note place="margin">Rom. 2.</note> 
               <hi>Qui iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicas alterum teipſum condemnas,</hi> Thou that doeſt iudge an other man thou doeſte condempne thy ſelfe, for thou thy ſelfe doeſt com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mytte
<pb facs="tcp:173926:48"/> the ſame crymes that thou reprehendes in an other man. But they wyll ſaye agayne, that that can not be ſo, for they be not pree<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtes, vnto that I aunſwere, that then they be no chryſten menne for euery true chriſten man is a preeſt as the ſcripture doth witneſſe:<note place="margin">Apoc. 5. 1. Pet. 2.</note> 
               <hi>Vos eſtis regale ſacerdotium gens ſancta.</hi> you are a preeſtly kyngdome, and a holy people. Alſo it is ſayd vnto Chriſt: Thou haſt redemed vs by thy blood out of all kynredes and tonges, and peoples, and nations: and haſte made vs vnto our god kynges, and preeſtes, and we ſhall raygne on the earth. yet you muſt not thynke, that euery man is a preeſt, ſo that he ſholde miniſtre y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſacramentes, or interprete &amp; teach goddes worde: but euery man is a preeſt as he is a kynge. He is a kynge for bycauſe that where as
<pb facs="tcp:173926:48"/> he was a ſeruaunt and bondman vnto the deuell, ſyn, and the fleſhe, by Chriſte he is nowe delyuered, &amp; they be throwen vnder his feete: that they no longer ſholde rule hym: but of the contrary he ſholde keape in ſubiection, and oppreſſe them, ſo ofte as they do aſſaute hym: as ſaynt Paule doth ſaye: <hi>Ne regnet peccatum in mortali cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pore veſtro.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Rom. 6.</note> Let not ſyn raygne in your mortall body, ſo that ye obey it accordyng to the deſyres therof: nother gyue you your membres vnto ſynne, to be weapons of vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ryghtwyſenes: but gyue your ſel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ues vnto god, as they y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> be deade, are become lyuyng: and your me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bres vnto god, to be weapons of rightwyſneſſe: for ſynne ſhall not haue power ouer you: euen ſo eue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry chriſten man is a preeſt, that he ſholde kyll and put to deathe his
<pb facs="tcp:173926:49"/> owne affections, uſtes, and deſy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>res: and ſholde offre vp vnto god his body a ſacrifice, that is lyuely and acceptable vnto god:<note place="margin">Rom. 12.</note> as ſaint Paule ſaith. Notwithſtandynge that this is the dewtie of euery chryſten man, &amp; vnto the perfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mance of this, is euery man eue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſo ſtreyghtly bounde, as the preeſt is to his cure: yet many doo gyue them ſelues (and ſpecyally theſe that thus rayle and crye out of preeſtes) vnto idelneſſe, eatynge, drynkyng, and banketting, rather to encorage and to prouoke the lu<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſtes &amp; deſyres of theyr fleſhe, then to quenche and to oppreſſe them: &amp; rather wyllyngly to gyue them ſelues agayne into the ſeruyce of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> deuell, then to withſtand his aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaultes, they do ſpende their time, at dyſe &amp; cardes, with ſuche other (as they call the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>) paſtimes whiche
<pb facs="tcp:173926:49"/> ben occaſyon of great contention, debate, and ſtrife, and bringe with them great othes, and periurie.</p>
            <p>They haue alſo co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>monly in theyr mouthes ſo fylthie, and vnclenlye communication, as chriſten eares wolde not wyllyngly heare, &amp; yet they lyuynge after this vngodlye rate &amp; faſhion, flatering, and plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſynge well them ſelues, doo crye out with open mouth of preeſtes, as ſuche as were not worthye to lyue: this wold not be ſo brethren, but rather firſt take the ende of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> wallet that hanges on your backe with your owne faultes, &amp; turne it before your face, and ſo eſpye and amende your owne lyues, when ye be admoniſhed therof: and then yf ye ſe other preeſtes offende, you may rebuke them: but yet ſo, that ye do not paſſe the bondes of bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therly loue. And co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſider with your
<pb facs="tcp:173926:50"/> ſelfes whervpon thoccaſyon doth ryſe, that there be in theſe dayes ſo many naughty preeſtꝭ, many there be (it can not be denyed) whiche of theyr owne wilfull naughtyneſſe, do lyue vnworthy theyr vocation: yet this I wyll ſay agayne, that a greate ſorte mo do runne amyſſe, by the meanes of temporall men: for yf a preeſt can flatter ſmothly, yf he wyll wynke or rather laugh at your vices, yf he wyl keape you company at bankettynge, diſyng and cardynge, runne with you of huntynge and hawkynge, whiche thynges drawe after them al kind of vices, he ſhall be called a good felowe, &amp; on ſuche ye wyll beſtowe your benefices, yf money wyll let you gyue them frely. Theſe dayes of ours (as touchinge preſtes) be muche lyke vnto the tyme that we ſpake of now, when as the Iewes
<pb facs="tcp:173926:50"/> ſent from Hieruſalem to Iohn<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>: for as Ioſephus doth teſtifie,<note place="margin">14. Anti. Ioſeph. 8.</note> after y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> (by the great contention had be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>twene Ariſtobolus and Hyrchanꝰ his brother) Pompey y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Romayne had entred in to Iheruſalem, and polluted the temple of god, there was neyther reſpecte had of the trybe of Leui,<note place="margin">15. Ioſe 2.</note> nor of the ſtocke of Aaron: but thoſe that were of leeſt eſtimation, and mooſt vnworthy that dignite, were choſen to be hye preeſtes: Euen ſo Pompeye this Romaine, that is to ſay, Couetouſ<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nes, that was wont to raygne at Rome, hathe inuaded vs, and is entred into the hartes of menne, whiche ſholde be temples of god, and ſo polluted them, that yf a ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> were as well learned as euer was Salamon,<note place="margin">1. Cor. 6. 2. Cor. 6.</note> and as vertuouſe in lyuynge as euer was Samuell, he ſhall ſpede of lyuynge or bene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fyce,
<pb facs="tcp:173926:51"/> but at a fewe temporal mens handes (ſome be good or elles god forbyd) without money: but rather his learnynge ſhall be called foo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lyſhnes, &amp; his vertuouſe lyfe hy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pocriſie. But of the contrary part yf he brynge money, without any regarde, yea or mention of eyther learnyng or vertue, he ſhalbe ſure to ſpeade. This Romiſh monſter, I meane couetouſnes, hath ſo in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flamed and ſet a fyre (as I haue ſayd) the hartes of men, that they do not refuſe,<note place="margin">Rom. 7. Acto. 8.</note> as S. Paule ſaith, to ſell them ſelues to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> deuell, vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der ſyn (for Symoni ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> be no leſſe then perditio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, both to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> vyer &amp; the ſeller) ſo greatly be we gyue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to lu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cre &amp; to gaynes, but what ſhall it profyt a man to gayne all y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> world yf he looſe his owne ſoule, ſayth chriſt, yea let Chriſte ſay what he wyll, that is a thinge we regarde
<pb facs="tcp:173926:51"/> not we haue him moch in our mou<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>thes and co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>munication (as it doth become vs) but in our lyfe and con<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>uerſation we do plainlye declare y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> in very dede we do nothing eſteme him, for our lyues doo nothynge agree with his worde or commau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dementes: we call hym father, and heauenly father, but we do not vſe oure ſelues towardes hym as lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uynge chyldren, yea we call hym y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> lorde and the lyuynge lord, but we do nothynge leſſe then ſhewe oure ſelues obediente ſeruauntes vnto hym: god ſaythe by his prophette Malachie. <hi>Si ego pater:</hi>
               <note place="margin">Malach. 1</note> 
               <hi>vbi eſt ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nor meus: Si ego dominus? vbi eſt ti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mor meus.</hi> yf I be your father wher is the honoure that ye gyue vnto me, yf I be your lorde where is my feare, that ſhulde be in you. And ſurely I do thynke y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> this queſtyo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, myght neuer better haue ben aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked
<pb facs="tcp:173926:52"/> then nowe in oure dayes, for the feare of god is clearely gonn<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> out of mennes hartes, in ſo muche that I doo feare that there be ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny that ſaye in theyr hartes, there is no god. And that thynge dothe moue me ſo to thinke, whiche mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued Dauid to ſaye.<note place="margin">Spal. 1.</note> 
               <hi>Dixit inſipiens in corde ſuo non eſt deus.</hi> The folyſh ſayde in his hart there is no god, whiche thynge Dauid doth proue after this ſorte, they be corrupte &amp; abhominable in their ſtudies and inuentions, there is not amonge theim that doth good, no not one, they haue al runne out of the way, and be vnprofitable, their throte is an open graue, they vſe their ton<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges to dyſceate and crafte, the ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nom of Aſpis is vnder theyr lyp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pes, whoſe mouthe is full of cur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſynge, euell ſayenges, and bytter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes, theyr feete be ſwyfte to ſhedde
<pb facs="tcp:173926:52"/> bloode, deſtruction and myſchief is in theyr wayes, and they haue not knowen the waye of peace, and after he addes the cauſe hereof, ſay<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>inge, the feare of god is not before theyr eyes, nowe we may thus ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther an argument w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> Dauid, now men in our dayes lyue after this ſame ſorte, drowned in the ſame vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, wherfore y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> feare of god is not before theyr eyes, and where it is not, there is no wyſedeme for.<note place="margin">Spal. 1<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> 
               <hi>Initi<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>um Sapientiae timor domini.</hi> The be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginning of wyſedome: is the feare of our Lorde: Therfore what ſo euer they ſpeake with theyr mouth outwardly, they ſay with them ſel<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ues in their hartes there is no god for if we did thincke w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> our ſelues that there is a god, whiche wyl re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>warde vertuous liuinge as he pro<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>miſeth that he wyll doo, and pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nyſhe the wycked for ſynne as he
<pb facs="tcp:173926:53"/> doth threte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, if that hope of reward dyd worke nothynge with vs, yet feare of puniſhment, ſholde make vs ſomewhat to refrayne, &amp; apply our ſelues to godlines: but now I wyl retourne, and proceade in the text it foloweth. <hi>Vt interrogarent e<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Tu quis es?</hi> That they ſholde aſke him, what art thou. Here maye we note two thinges. Fyrſt y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſiniſtral, and arrogant faſhyon of theſe pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtes, whiche wolde not aſke hym directly yf he were chriſt, although they were ſent for that pourpoſe: but diſdaynedly dydde aſke hym, what arte thou? whiche doeſt take vpon the to baptyſe and to teache the people newe rytes. Agayne we may note the crafte of the deuel which euen as he dyd deceaue hym ſelfe in heauen, ſayenge y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> he wold<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> aſſende aboue the heauens and be yl<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e the hyeſt,<note place="margin">Iſai. 14.</note> and as he dydde diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceyue
<pb facs="tcp:173926:53"/> oure fore parentes in para<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dyſe, ſayenge vnto them, that yf they wolde eate of the aple, whiche was inhibited, then theyr eyes ſholde be opened,<note place="margin">Gene. 3.</note> and they ſholde be lyke vnto god, knowenge good and euyl: Euen ſo he goeth about by theſe Iewes to deceaue Iohn<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> here in earth, that he ſhold goo a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout to be lyke vnto his mayſter, and to take vnto hym the glorie dewe vnto his mayſter Chriſt: but Iohn<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> was no reede, that he could be moued with any flatterynge or temptation, ſo that the deuell and his membres in temptyng of hym loſt theyr labour. The deuell hath fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the begynnynge vſed alwayes this craft and ſnare, in deceauing of men, and yet ſtyll doth vſe: and yet man is ſoo dull and groſſe of hym ſelfe, and ſo negligent in pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uydinge thoſe thynges whiche he
<pb facs="tcp:173926:54"/> for his owne ſoule health. And in auoyding of the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>trary, that with this olde beate and ſnare many be dayly trapped &amp; poyſonid. Fyrſte to begynne with the byſſhoppe of Rome, whiche dyd profeſſe to be <hi>Seruus ſeruorum dei.</hi> The ſeruaunt of the ſeruauntes of god: but he had this beate layde for hym, and ſwalowed it: wherfore he wolde be <hi>Dominus dominorum.</hi> Lorde &amp; mai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter of lordes: for he dyd vſurpe &amp; ſubdewe vnto hym al chriſten na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cions, with kynges &amp; emperours, and ouer them wolde be ruler and head. And yf a man ſholde haue moued this queſtion to hym, whi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>che was moued to Iohn<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, <hi>Tu quis es?</hi> what arte thou? whiche doeſt thus take vpon y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> to be lorde ouer kynges and emperours. He wold haue aunſwered that he had b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> Chriſtes vicar in earth: when as
<pb facs="tcp:173926:54"/> there coulde be nothyng more co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary, then was his faſhyon and vſage, vnto the behauour of our ſauyour Chriſte, whyle he was in earth: For as Chriſt dyd excell in humilite, ſo dyd he excell in pryde, and exaltynge of hym ſelfe. But thankes be to god, his combe is ſomwhat cutte, &amp; we for our parte be delyuered from his tyranny: and haue hym for our chiefe head vnder Chriſt in earth, whome ſcri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pture dothe apoynte vs to haue, that is our kynges maieſtie. yet notwithſtandynge, that we be de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lyuered from this Romyſhe bon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dage, there be amongeſt vs yet a great meany which dayly be poy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſened with this ſame venim of the deuel, that he was poyſened with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all. I meane pryde of herte, ſo that they wyll not be co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tent with theyr owne ſtate and condition, but do
<pb facs="tcp:173926:55"/> ſtudye and labour by all meanes to be lyke vnto theyr mayſters: whiche thynge I wolde to god we wolde banyſhe and throwe awaye with the byſſhop of Rome: &amp; that euery ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> wold be co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tent to walke worthely in his owne vocation, where vnto he is called,<note place="margin">Ephe. 4.</note> with all loulyneſſe &amp; gentylneſſe of mynde, as ſaynt Paule gyueth counſayl. But as I ſayd of chriſte, ſo I may ſaye of ſaynt Paule, we do in oure mouth, and in wordes greatly ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>toll laude, and prayſe ſaynt Paul and we crye out of the deuyll, and defie hym. But when as ſaynte Paule bydded vs do one thynge, and the deuel doth alure vs to the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>trary: we do in dede forſake the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>maundementes of ſaynt Paule and do folowe the counſaile of the deuell. Saint Paule ſtandeth on the one ſyde and ſaith: let nothyng
<pb facs="tcp:173926:55"/> be done by co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tention or by vayne glory, but that thorowe mekenes of mynde,<note place="margin">Philip. 2.</note> euery man eſteme an o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther better then him ſelfe, the oe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uell ſtandeth on the other ſyde, &amp; he ſaith be contentious, and vayn glorious, &amp; let euery man thynke him ſelfe better then an other, this intiſement and perſwaſion of the deuyll we do gladly enbrace, no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thinge regardynge the preceptes of ſaynt Paule. notwithſtanding the great fauour and eſtimation that we prentende in our wordes to haue hym in, we nede not to go farre to ſeke examples for the try<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all or proue hereof, may we not ſee a ſeruynge man, hauynge not paſt foure nobles, or .xl. s. wages to lyue vpon, ſo gorgiouſly appare<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led in his geſture, and behauoure of his bodye: in his paaſe, and go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ynge ſo vſe him ſelfe, as yf he were
<pb facs="tcp:173926:56"/> a man of ſubſtaunce, yea an Eſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quier, or a knyght, and yf a man wolde haue experience further of his maners &amp; conditions, he ſhall fynde hym ſtoute in wordes, lybe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall ye prodigall in expenſes, and all together gyuen to preferre him<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſelf vnto other men, and yf a man dare be ſo bolde, as to moue vnto him this queſtyon, that was mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued to Ihon<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. <hi>Tu quis es?</hi> What an chou? y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> thus ſtoutely takeſt vpon the. He wyll ſtreyght auaunce him ſelfe, and be ready to brawle and to fyght with him, ſo that the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phete Dauyd may be thought to haue ſpoken of ſuch when he ſayd. <hi>Vani filii hominum,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Spal. 61.</note> 
               <hi>mendaces filii ho<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>minum:</hi> The chyldren of menne be vayne, the chyldren of men be ly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers, thus flatterynge them ſelues, thinkynge them ſelues more wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy then other men, yea they be
<pb facs="tcp:173926:56"/> more vayne then vanite the ſelfe, if they were wayed therewith in a pare of balaunces. yet not onelye theſe be ſtraungled in this ſnare, but alſo many other. A prentyſe, whiche is bound by promyſe, ſuer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties, indentures to be obediente to his mayſter for certayne yeares to do him trewe &amp; dylygent ſeruyce: within fewe yeares after that he hathe taſted of this beate, gyuen hym of the deuell, he beginneth to ſtande in his owne conceyte, to diſ<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>dayne his mayſter, to neglecte his office, and dewtie, yea nothinge to regarde, neyther his owne profyt, nor the profyt of his mayſter: yf he be gentlye admoniſſhed, he wyll not regarde it, but rather wyll laugh therat: yf he be with ſharpe wordes reprehended, he wyl make aunſwere agayne chorliſhly: and if his mayſter goo aboute to cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>recte
<pb facs="tcp:173926:57"/> hym, he wyll withſtande hym yea &amp; take the ſtaff by thende: &amp; if this queſtion be propou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ded vnto him. <hi>Tu quis es.</hi> what art thou, that wyll not be obediente to thy ma<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter, he wyll aunſwere ſtreyght I am to good to do ſeruyce to ſuche a mayſter, and theſe ſpecially wyll haue in their handes the new teſta<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ment, and they wyll talke muche of the ſcripture, and goddes word, and yet wyll not learne therof to be obedient, and gentle vnto theyr mayſters: they wyll taulke muche of Paul, and yet it doth nothinge moue them that Paule in ſo many places doth beete and incoulcate in, that ſeruauntes ſholde be obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dient, and faythfull to their may<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters, as vnto Tite. <hi>Seruos hortare vt ſuis dominis pareant.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Tit. 2</note> Exhort and moue ſeruauntes that they do o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bey theyr mayſters y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> they pleaſe
<pb facs="tcp:173926:57"/> theym in all thinges, that they be no aunſweres, gyuinge one word for an other, that they doo not w<hi rend="sup">t</hi>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>drawe their mayſters goods, but that they ſhewe all faythfulnes, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> they may adourne the doctrine of god our ſauyour in all thynges. Likewyſe ſaint Petre ſaith let ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uauntes be ſubiecte vnto theyr mayſters, with feare,<note place="margin">1. Pet. 2.</note> not only to thoſe that be good and, gentle, but alſo to thoſe y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> be frowarde, moche lyke vnto theſe ſtubbarue prenty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes, be chyldren of this tyme: whi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>che after they be come to certayne yeres of age, they be alſo taken in this ſnare of the deuel, and begyn to pleaſe them ſelues, and wyll no longer be in ſubiection to theyr parentes, and excepte they be cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>recte by tyme, and holden vnder, it wyll come to paſſe that the wyſe man ſayth.<note place="margin">Eccle. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>0.</note> 
               <hi>Equus indomitus euadit
<pb facs="tcp:173926:58"/> durus, &amp; filiꝰ remiſſus, euadit praecep<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </hi> A horſe that is not broken by time groweth chorlyſhe, and a chylde that is ſette at lybertie, runneth headlynges, yea into all kynde of vices. And this cometh to paſſe for the mooſt parte by the remiſnes of parentes: whiche with to greate lenite and te<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>dernes, do brynge vp theyr chyldre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> without feare or cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rection: For as the ſame wyſe man ſaith: Correct thy chylde, and thou ſhalte make hym feare the: playe with him &amp; he wyll make the ſad: laugh not w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> him, leſt thou weape with hym: but holde downe his necke, whyle he is yonge, &amp; correct hym in his youth, leſte he growe ſtoubburne, and wyl not obey the, and tourne to thy grefe and heui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe. And yf a man ſhold aſke any of theſe yonge men (whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> they wyll not be obedient to theyr parentes)
<pb facs="tcp:173926:58"/> this queſtyon afore mencyoned: what art thou? that wylt not obey thy father and mother, and be ru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led by them. They wyl make aun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer &amp; ſaye: I am nowe no chylde, I am come to the yeares of diſcre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, I knowe what is for me, and what is agaynſt me. Heare howe that the deuell hath not onely ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> in his ſnare, but alſo doth leade them forth whither him lyſt: theachyng them to excuſe them, &amp; to defende theyr faulte: whiche is worſe then the cryme it ſelfe. If I ſholde after this ſorte, runne tho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rowe all and ſynguler ſtates and condicions of men, it ſhold appere playnly, how that in euery condi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cion, very many do labour (as I haue ſayde before) to be lyke vnto theyr mayſters, and but a few wyl come vnto chriſt, to be his ſcolers: although he crye earneſtly:<note place="margin">Math. 11.</note> come
<pb facs="tcp:173926:59"/> vnto me all you that labour, and be laden, and I ſhal refreſhe you, and you ſhall fynde reſte for your ſoules. But the reſte of the ſoule is not the thyng that we regarde, of the body &amp; the pleaſours ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of is all our mynde: wherfore we do wyllyngly gyue eare to the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uell: mouynge vs to the reſte and pleaſures of the body, &amp; do ſtoppe our eares, &amp; wyll not heare Chriſt, mouyng vs to ſeke the reſte of the ſoule. Wherfore we be not content with oure owne proper vocation, but one doth diſdayne, and enuye an other: not beynge content that other ſhold excell vs in any thing This pouder of the deuell ſpryn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kled in our hartes, is y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> cauſe not only of the enormyte of theſe that I haue ſpoken on before: But alſo of all other of the ſame ſort. This is the cauſe that priuate perſons
<pb facs="tcp:173926:59"/> do grudge and diſdayne with co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon officers: and that the officers agayne do deſpiſe thoſe that be vnder them, laborynge ſtyll to go alofte &amp; to be hygher in promotio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> &amp; dignite: herof it cometh y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> the lay people do grudge agaynſt y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> clear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gye, diſdaynynge to be taught of them, challengynge vnto them ſel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ues a more perfaicte knowledge in ſcripture then the other haue, and ſaye that the miſteries of ſcriptu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>res be opened vnto them, by, I can not tell, what ſpirite, ſo that if they haue redde ouer once the newe te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtament in englyſhe, they wyll not ſticke to enterprete the mooſt dar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keſt places in ſcripture, contrarye both to the auncient and mooſt ho<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>lye doctors, and alſo the decrees of the churche. And if this queſtio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> be moued vnto them, that was mo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ued vnto Iohn<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. <hi>Tu quis es?</hi> What
<pb facs="tcp:173926:60"/> arte thou that thus doeſt take vp<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>pon the to interprete ſcripture, con<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>trary to the churche, and the doc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tors therof: he wyll ſtreyght make aunſwere, and ſay I am one whoſe eyes it hath pleaſed god to haue opened that I ſhold ſe his truthe: the churche hath erred, the doctors haue ben diſceaued, as I knowe I my ſelf can not be, for I am ſuere that I am one of the predeſtinate and electe, &amp; therof they wyl large<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, and lyberally diſpute and rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, not knowynge what the ſcrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture doth meane by predeſtination and election: for they ſeme to make it ſuche a thynge, as and if god ſhold appoynt certayne out by the heade, and ſaye theſe I wyll ſhalbe ſaued, howe ſo euer they do lyue. And ſholde ſhette an other ſort ou<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> of the doores, and ſaye: they ſhold be damned if they lyued neuer ſoo
<pb facs="tcp:173926:60"/> vertuouſly: whiche thynge either to ſaye or thinke is a deteſtable er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rour, and a deuellyſhe opinion. I do thinke that Paul knew no ſuch election; although they gether of hym, many places for the confir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mation therof, whiche trulye vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtonde, doth nothinge make for theyr purpoſe, for he ſayth.<note place="margin">2. Timo. 2</note> 
               <hi>Omnia ſuffero propter electos, vt &amp; ipſi ſalu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tem conſequantur.</hi> I do ſuffre all thynges for the electe, that they al<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſo may obteyne ſaluation. Lyke<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wyſe ſaynt Petre ſayth,<note place="margin">2. Pet. 1.</note> miniſter in youre fayth vertue, in vertue knowledge, in knowledge tempe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raunce, in temperaunce pacience, in pacience godlines, in godlines brotherly loue, in brotherlye loue, generall loue: for if theſe thinges be plentuouſly in you, they wyll not let you be idel, nor vnfrutefull in the knowledge of oure Lorde
<pb facs="tcp:173926:61"/> Ieſus Chriſte, but he that lacketh theſe thinges, is blynde and gro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peth for the waye with his hande, and hathe forgotten that he was clenſhed fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> his olde ſynnes, wher<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>fore breatherne ſayth ſaynt Petre gyue the more diligence, to make your callynge, and election ſure for if ye do theſe thinges ye ſhall not fall: and by theſe meanes ſhall there be plenteouſly miniſtred vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to you an entraunce in to the euer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laſtynge kyngdome of our lorde &amp; ſauyour Ieſus Chriſte. Agayne ſaynt Paul ſayth in a great mans houſe,<note place="margin">2. Timo. 2</note> are not only veſſels of gold and ſyluer, but alſo of wood and earthe, ſome for honour, and ſome to dyſhonour but if a man purge himſelfe from theſe, he ſhalbe a veſſel ſanctified vnto honour mete for the lorde, and prepared vnto al good workes. Now for gods ſake
<pb facs="tcp:173926:61"/> bretherne, let vs leue theſe fanta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſies, and heare what the prophete Dauyd ſayth vnto ſuche that pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſumptuouſly doo talke of ſuche thinges as they be ignorant in, &amp; lyue after theyr luſtes: <hi>Intelligite inſipientes in populo,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Pſal. 93.</note> 
               <hi>&amp; ſtulti aliqua<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>do ſapite.</hi> Vnderſtande you vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wyſe amonges the people, &amp; you fooles at the length learne wiſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome: Do you thynke that he that made the eare, doth not heare theſe your preſumptuouſe wordes. Do you thynke that he that made the eye, doth not ſe your naughty ly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ues. Do you thynke that he that doth correcte people, wyll not pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nyſhe you. And it folowes in the ſame pſalme: Our Lorde dothe knowe the thought and imagina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions of man; y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> they be but vaine. Let vs therfore learne a leſſon of the good honeſt woman Anne, the
<pb facs="tcp:173926:62"/> wyfe of Helchena, whiche ſaithe thus in her ſonge:<note place="margin">1. Regi. 2.</note> 
               <hi>Nolite multipli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>care loqui ſublimia gloriantes.</hi> Do not multiplye in ſpeakynge of prowd wordes glorieng. Let olde thinges depart from your mouth for god is the lorde of knowledge, and your thought and imagina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions be manifeſt vnto hym. yea he is not onely the god of know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge: but as Dauid ſaith: <hi>Deus vl<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tionum dominus.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Pſal. 93.</note> God is the lorde of puniſhementes: and ſpecyally he wyll punyſhe the prowde. Let vs therfore deare bretherne con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſider with our ſelues, that theſe fancies and imaginations of our worthynes, be nothynge elles but ſnares of the deuell, wherwith he hath from the begynnynge decey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued our elders: and with the ſame goeth about to deceyue vs alſo. And where as we do ꝑceyue them
<pb facs="tcp:173926:62"/> tyckle vs: let vs moue this que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtyon vnto our ſelues: <hi>Tu quis es?</hi> what arte thou? And conſyder in our owne hartes truely and dyli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gently, what we be in very dede, and how vnkyndely we haue vſed oure ſelfes, towardes ſo kynde a god and a lord: which hath gyuen vs all ſuche giftes, as we haue, without any deſeruinge of oure parte. And then ſtreyght of this ſhall folowe an other queſtyon, whiche is this. <hi>Quare ſuperbis terra &amp; cinis?</hi> why arte thou proud thou earth and aſhes? which thyng no doubt Iohn<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> dyd conſyder: wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore neyther the craft of the deuel, nor the flatery of the Iewes could moue hym to take, when it was offered vnto hym, the glory dewe to his mayſter Chriſt: But he dyd confeſſe and he dyd not denye. He confeſſed that he was not, and he
<pb facs="tcp:173926:63"/> dyd not denye what he was: and ſo it dyd become hym, whiche was the meſſengar of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> trought it ſelf, to declyne nothyng at all from the trought. And vndoubtedly that is the dewty of thoſe that be prea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chers of goddes worde, playnely, and at all tymes to declare and ſpeake the trought, without any reſpect of the pleaſour or diſplea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſour of men: yea &amp; alſo of all thoſe that doth profeſſe Chriſt, which is the ſelfe trought, to be gyrded as ſaint Paule ſaith:<note place="margin">Ephe. 6.</note> with the gyrdle of trought: ſo that at no tyme thei go without the compas therof. But I do thynke, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> now in theſe dayes, many do not ſtudye, howe they maye kepe them within the compas of this gyrdle: but rather how they may broſt out, and ſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cyally marchauntes, and occupy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers of London. whiche, as it is
<pb facs="tcp:173926:63"/> ſayd, yf a man come to them, and deſire to haue of theyr ware, as a peece of clooth or chamlet, they wyll ſtreyght ſhewe hym one, and ſay, that that is for hym: and yf he deſyre to ſe a better, they wyll ſaye agayne, yea: and confirme it with greate othes, that it is cleare the beſte in his ſhoppe, and that there is not a better in London. Nowe let hym bye it, and ſo departe: and yf an other ſe it, &amp; thervpon come to the ſame marchaunt, for ſuche an other, he wyll ſtreyght ſhewe hym one, &amp; ſet it out after the ſame ſorte, as he dyd the other: and yf the byer deſyre to ſe a better, and ſaye that ſuch a man had a good peece of hym, he wyll anſwer with great othes, &amp; ſay: This is worth thre of thother. yf that this faſhio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> be vſed amonge you Londoners, as many ſaye it is, ye do playnlye
<pb facs="tcp:173926:64"/> declare that you haue a contrarye ſpirite, to this ſpirite. That Iohn<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> hadde, his was a true ſpirit, and of god: yours is a lyinge ſpirite, and of the deuell. But lette vs g<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> forthe with the texte.</p>
            <p>He dyd confeſſe &amp; ſayde, I am not Chriſte: omittynge thoſe thinges, that they aſked in wordes, he aun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwereth briefly to thintent of theyr mynde, vſynge fewe wordes, for when a man begynneth w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> longe circu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſtaunces fetched farre, from the matter it ſelf, it is to be feared that there is ſome ſubtilte or craft meant therin, which Iohn<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> did not knowe, he anſwered therefore to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> thinge it ſelfe, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> they went about, they aſked him who he was, mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nynge yf he weare Chriſt, nowe he doth not aunſwere to the queſty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on what he was himſelf, but to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> intente therof ſayeng, he was not
<pb facs="tcp:173926:64"/> Chryſte, whiche thynge when as they harde they weare no more earneſt w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> him in it, for althoughe they dyd neither fauoure him, nor his doctrine, yet they thoughte he was worthy to be beleued: ſuch is the ſtrengthe, and nature of ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tue, that it doth ingender: yea eue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> in a mans ennemyes, an opinion of conſtauncie and faythfulneſſe. Then they dyd remembre the teſti<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>monie of Malachie the prophete, as touchinge the comynge of He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lyas,<note place="margin">Mala. 4.</note> which ſholde go before chriſt to prepare his wayes: wherefore they thinke, ſeyng that they knew that Chriſt was at hand, and hea<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>rynge Iohn<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> denye that he was Chriſt, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> he is Helyas. They aſke him therfore, what then art thou, Helyas? And he ſayde: I am not. Chriſte ſayde that Iohn<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> was He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bras. Ihon<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> him ſelf doth denye it:
<pb facs="tcp:173926:65"/> and both be true. The Iewes aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked Iohn<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, whether he weare in perſon Helyas Theſbites,<note place="margin">4. Regi. 2.</note> whiche was taken vp in the fyrye charet. And vnto that Iohn<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> aunſwered, and ſayde he is not. Yet not with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtandynge he had commune with Helyas auſterite of lyuinge, bold<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nes in reprehendynge of noughty<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nes, in ſpirite and offyce. For as Helyas Theſbytes ſhall come be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the latter commynge of oure ſauyour Chriſt: euen ſo dyd Iohn<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> come before the fyrſte commynge, &amp; both to gyue warning to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple to prepare his wayes. Wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore Chriſte ſayd trewely y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> Iohn<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> was Helyas: &amp; alſo Iohn<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſayeng y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> he was not Helyas. They aſked him then. Art y<hi rend="sup">u</hi> the ꝓphet? And he ſaid no. They do not aſke him ſim<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ply, whither he were a prophete or no: but yf he were y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> notable pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phet,
<pb facs="tcp:173926:65"/> of whom Moſes dyd ſpeake ſayeng:<note place="margin">Act. 7. Deut, 18.</note> your Lord god ſhal ſtirre vp among you of your owne bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therne a prophete lyke vnto me, &amp; ye ſhall heare hym: and ſo Iohn<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> anſwered truely, that he was not that prophete. For Chriſt hym ſelf was he. They ſaye therfore vnto him. What art thou? that we may gyue an anſwere to them that ſent vs. What ſayeſt thou of thy ſelfe. Theſe preeſtes &amp; Leuites thought them ſelfe cunnynge in ſcripture, that if there had ben any mention made therein of the commynge of Iohn, they ſholde haue knowen. wherfore now they ſay vnto hym: what ſayeſte thou of thy ſelfe: as who wolde ſaye: ſcripture dothe make no mention of the: therfore thou muſt declare thy ſelfe what thou art, ſuche is the learnynge &amp; wyſdome of man, when he ſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>deth
<pb facs="tcp:173926:66"/> in his owne conceyt, and thinketh that he can co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>prehende all myſte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries, that then it turneth vnto ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry folyſhnes.<note place="margin">1. Cor. 1 Iſai. 29.</note> For <hi>Infatuauit dens ſa<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>pientiam huius mundi &amp; intellig<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tiam intelligentiu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> reiecit.</hi> God hath made folyſh the wyſedome of this worlde, and hath reiected and caſt away the learnynge of them that thinke them ſelues lerned, and do not acknowledge and rendre dew thankes vnto hym, that is the gyuer therof. As it maye appere in theſe preeſtes, and Leuites, whiche weare caſt in theyr owne turne: for Ihon<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> in his aunſwere doth bewraye theyr ignoraunce, ſhewynge that Iſai the prophete had propheſied of his commynge. He anſwereth therfore and faith. I am the voyce of a <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>ye<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> in wyl<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dernes, to prepare the waye of our lorde, as I faithe prophete ſayde.
<pb facs="tcp:173926:66"/> I ſayde before, that Iohn<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> was no reede, that is not vnconſtant, as it doth heare appere more playnly for he doth continewe ſtedfaſtlye in the humilitie and lowelynes of ſpirite, which in his aunſwere ma<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>keth no mention of his owne wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thines, althoughe he were more ex<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>cellent then a ꝓphete,<note place="margin">Math. 11.</note> &amp; none more excellent then he amo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>geſt the chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren of wome<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. Neither he ſpeketh of the nobilitie of his ſtocke: al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though he was come of a greate ſtocke in dead, but he telleth what he is by offyce, forgettynge (as ſaynt Paule ſayth) thoſe thinges that were behinde him,<note place="margin">Philip. 3.</note> loking all together at thoſe thynges that were before him, he foloweth ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cordynge to the marke that was ſet him vp: that he may get the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>warde of the heuenly vocation: which leſſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>: I wolde to god y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> all
<pb facs="tcp:173926:67"/> men in theſe dayes wolde learne of Iohn<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, &amp; ſpecially common offy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cers, which as it may be thought, be altogether vnlyke vnto Iohn<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> for he (that he might more faithful<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ly and truely execute his offyce, ac<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>cording to the wyl of his mayſter) dyd forſake his parentes, w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> their hole familie, yea &amp; his patrimonie if that he ſholde haue had any, as it is moſt like he ſholde, he dyd al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo forſake and flye from idelnes, and the reſt of the bodye, with de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lycate fare, and gorgious apparel he dyd take vpon him greate pay<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nes, and labours, lyuynge hardly clothed in heare,<note place="margin">Math. 3.</note> he dyd lyberallye and boldlye reprehende offenders of all ſortes, he hunted after the fa<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>uour of no manne, nor feared no mans threatnynges, but officers in theſe our dayes, be of a contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rye ſorte, for they doo not regarde
<pb facs="tcp:173926:67"/> nor requyre an office, but for this ende, that they may promote and exalte their frendes, enlarge theyr patrimonie, lyue idely, fare dyly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cately, be appareled gorgiouſly, &amp; to bringe theſe thynges to pas, they flatter greate menne, the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempne, ye and polle poore men, if a ryche man of any parte do his dewtie, that he is commaunded to do, of his lorde, or kynge, by them he ſhalbe prayſed, yea and well re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>warded, but if the poore man do it with neuer ſo greate dylygence, there ſhall no worde be ſpoken of it: agayne if the poore man therin offende, he ſhall be ſtreyghtly pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nyſhed, if the riche man omitte the hole, eyther the offycers mouthes ſhalbe ſtopped with a bribe, or els for feare of diſpleaſure, they wyll let it ſlyp, ſo that in them it ſhall not be punyſſhed: theſe officers be
<pb facs="tcp:173926:68"/> be ſuche as Dauyd ſpeakes on in his ſpalme, where he ſayth, <hi>Homo cum in honore eſſet, non intellexit co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paratus eſt rumentis inſipientibus: &amp; ſimilis factus eſt illis.</hi> Man when he was promoted vnto dignite or of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fyce dyd not conſidre him ſelfe, he is compared to folyſhe brute bea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtes, and he is euen lyke vnto the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> in deade, for as the brute beaſte doth neither remember thynges paſt, nor conſyder thinges to come but gyue them ſelues altogether to theſe thinges that be preſente, euen ſoo theſe officers do, for they neyther remembre wherof they be come, nor what they haue ben, nor yet what they may come to, if they abuſe their office, and their may<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter take dyſpleaſure with them, but loke what thinge doth playſt them for the tyme, and that they enbrace: And wel they may be like<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ned
<pb facs="tcp:173926:68"/> vnto the noughtie ſeruaunt y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> chriſt ſpeaketh of which when his mayſter had made ouerſeer of his houſeholde,<note place="margin">Math. 24</note> and was gon vnto a ſtraunge contrye, ſayd with hym ſelf: It wyl belong or my mayſter come home agayne, and therefore he begonne to beate his fellow ſer<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>uauntes, to eate and drincke with dronckerdes, euen ſo theſe offy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cers do thinke with them ſelues, that theyr actes can not come to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> eares of their lorde, or kynge, but let them take hede, for as it is a co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>mon ſayenge. <hi>Multae ſunt Regum au<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tes, et oculi.</hi> Kynges haue manye eares, and eyes, and althoughe y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> they can keape their factes cloſe from the eares of a mortall kynge or lorde, yet they can not hyde the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> from him that is immortal:<note place="margin">Pſal. 33.</note> whoſe countenaunce is ouer all euell do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers. And he wyll come in that day that
<pb facs="tcp:173926:69" rendition="simple:additions"/> they leeſt weane, and that houre that they knowe not,<note place="margin">Math. 24</note> and wyll cut them into peces and gyue them theyr rewarde, w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> ypocrites, where ſhalbe waylynge ang knaſſhynge of tethe learne therfore you offy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cers, of Iohn<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to forget thoſe thin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges that be behynde you, that is the world with the pompe therof, and ſet youre eyes onelye vppon thoſe thinges that be before you, that is your dewtie, and that that doth pertayne to the faythfull per<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>formynge of your offices. And it ſhalbe ſayd vnto euery one of you well thou faythfull and good ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uant,<note place="margin">Math. 26.</note> thou haſt ben faythfull ouer a fewe thinges, I ſhall conſtitute y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ouer many entre into the ioye of thy mayſter for only that thynge dyd Iohn<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> regarde: wherefore <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e ſaith, that he is the voyce of a cry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er in wyldernes. Chriſt in the goſ<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>pell
<pb facs="tcp:173926:69"/> ſayth vnto his Apoſtles, whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> he ſent them of preachynge, it ſhal not be you that ſhall ſpeake, but the ſpyryte of my father ſhall ſpeake in you, lykewiſe dauyd in his ſpalmes ſayth.<note place="margin">Pſal. 44.</note> 
               <hi>Lingua mea ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lamus ſcribae, velociter ſcribentis.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>My tonge is the penne of a writer that writeth faſt, ſignifyenge that his pſalmes were not his, but they were the worke of the holy ghoſt: ſo Iohn<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> here ſayth he is the voyce of a cryer, as and if he ſholde ſaye, I ſpeake nothynge of myne owne heade, but I ſpeake thoſe thinges that be commaunded me of my mayſter to ſpeake, lyberally vtte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rynge thoſe thinges that my com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſion wylleth me to ſpeake, and nothinge ther vnto addynge.</p>
            <p>Wherfore if you reiecte my ſay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>inge ye do not reiecte me, but ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther hym that ſpeaketh in me, for
<pb facs="tcp:173926:70"/> I am but a voyce whereby as by an inſtrument Chriſt doth declare vnto you his wyll. A voyce of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> ſelfe is a ſounde that goeth before the worde, ſo that if the worde do not folowe, the voyce is a vayne thinge, as it were braſſe ſoundyng or a Cymball tincklynge. And ſo was Iohn<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the voyce of Chriſt the euerlaſtynge worde of the father without whom Iohn<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſholde haue ben a vayne thinge, but now that the worde Chriſt dyd folowe the voyce is not vayne, but rather as Dauyd ſaith. <hi>Vox domini in virtute vox domini in magnificentia.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Pſal. 28.</note> The voyce of our Lorde is in vertue y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> voyce of our Lorde is in pythe, &amp; in ſtrength, the voyce of the lorde that pulleth downe the high trees of Libanus, whiche in dead Iohn<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> dydde when he pulled downe the ſtoute hartes of the Iewes, ſo that
<pb facs="tcp:173926:70"/> by penaunce, they weare contente to be baptiſed of hym, yet it was not Iohn<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> that dyd it, but it was he which ſtode the laſt great daye, of the feaſt and cryed ſayenge,<note place="margin">Iohn<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. 7.</note> yf any man be a thyrſte let him come vnto me, and drincke: the Euan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gelyſt ſaith that he cryed, whiche was bicauſe he wolde haue euery man to heare him, that euery man might be ſaued,<note place="margin">1. Timo. 2</note> &amp; come to knowe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge of the truth, for it is not his wyl that any ſhold peryſh. Where<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>fore they erre whiche ſay, that of abſolute neceſſite ſome muſt nedes be damned, for ſaynt Paule ſayth. <hi>Periunt, pro eo ꝙ dilectionem verita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tis non receperunt,</hi>
               <note place="margin">2. Theſ. 2.</note> 
               <hi>in hoc vt ſalui fie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rent.</hi> They do periſhe, bicauſe they receiued not the loue of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> trueth, y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> they myght haue bene ſaued, but peraduenture ſome wyll obiecte, and ſaye if he wolde haue euerye
<pb facs="tcp:173926:71"/> man ſaued then they ſhalbe ſaued for who can reſiſte his wyll: vnto this is to be aunſwered that we muſt conſydre two wylles to be in in god, a wyll that goeth before &amp; an other that co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>meth after: by his fyrſte wyll he wolde haue all men to walke in his commaundemen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes: and ſo come to euerlaſtynge lyfe, but when he ſeeth the vnto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wardnes of thoſe that wyll folow their owne luſtes, and wyll not o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bey his commaundementes, then by his later wyl he wyl haue them puniſhed accordinge to their deſer<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tes: as for an exemple. A man ſet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth a tree in his garden, wyllyng that it ſhall growe there manye yeares for to bringe forth fruyte, now within fewe yeares when he ſeeth that it wyll brynge forthe none, he commaundeth by and by contrary to his firſt wyll, to cutte
<pb facs="tcp:173926:71"/> it downe ſayeng, where vnto doth it occupye the grounde in vayne. It is not vnlike vnto this, that is writen in the pſalme.<note place="margin">Pſat. 79.</note> 
               <hi>Vineam de Egipto tranſtuliſti.</hi> Thou haſte brought out of Egypte a vine. Thou haſte caſte out Gentyles, &amp; planted it, whiche vine (as the Pſalmis ſheweth to be breefe) for a tyme dyd greatly encreaſe and growe, ſo that the ſhadowe therof dyd couer the hylles, but after the hedge was pulled downe, and the wylde beaſtes did deſtroye it, and why,<note place="margin">Iſai. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> but bycauſe (as Eſaie ſayth) he loked y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> it ſholde haue brought grapes &amp; it brought out thornes, ſo that the fault was in it, and not in him: for god doth aſke by Eſaie and ſaythe: what ſholde I haue done to my vineyard, that I haue not done: truly nothynge. For as I haue ſayde, he cryeth vnto vs,
<pb facs="tcp:173926:72"/> wyllynge euery manne to amende his lyfe, and ſo to be ſaued. Yea he hath cryed in olde tyme by his pro<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>phettes, after by hym ſelfe, his Apoſtels and diſciples, and ſtyll crieth vnto this daye, by his prea<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>chers, but we ſtoppe oure eares &amp; wyll not heare, we be muche lyke vnto the people of London, which do heare after a ſorte. The belles of Paules, when they rynge to Matyns at mydnight, the belles do ſounde in theyr eares, yet they wyll not ryſe, but rather wyl tourne them on thother ſyde, and ſlepe agayne, for they thynke the daye is not as yet neare, euen ſoo do we heare the preachers of god, their voyce dothe ſounde in oure eares, but we will not ariſe from our noughty lyfe: but ſtyll ſlepe in ſynne thinkynge that the daye doth not drawe neare, when as we
<pb facs="tcp:173926:72"/> ſhall make accompte of our actes, but let vs not deceyue our ſelues, for ſaynt Paule ſayth, it is tyme for vs to ryſe from ſlepe, the night is paſt and the day draweth neare Nowe if the day were neare in the tyme of ſaynt Paule, that is .xv. hundreth yeare a goo we maye well thinke that it is nowe verye neare, lette vs therfore open oure eares and heare him cryenge: for yf we wyll not, we ſhall herafter crye, and he wyll not heare vs, but there ſhalbe other, that is to ſaye our noughty lyfe, and they vnto whom we haue done iniurye and wronge, accuſynge vs, and they ſhalbe hearde. wherfore if we wyll ſtoppe the eares of god, that he ſhall not here oure accuſars, we muſt here him when he cryeth, and alſo crye diligentely vnto hym by prayer, as Dauyd doth witnes of
<pb facs="tcp:173926:73"/> hym ſelfe that he dyd, ſayenge. <hi>De profundis clamaui ad te domine.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Pſal. 129.</note> Lord I haue cryed vnto the from the bothome of my harte, Lorde heare my voyce: and agayn. <hi>Labo raui clamans,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Pſal. 68.</note> I haue taken greate paynes in cryenge, ſo that I am horſe while I truſt in my lorde.</p>
            <p>But euen as we wyll not heare hym when he cryeth, ſo we be very neglygent in cryinge agayne to him. For ſurely I do thinke that ſyns the begynnynge of Chriſtes churche, there was neuer ſo lyttle prayer vſed among chriſten men, wherfore it may be well ſayd vnto vs, that ſaynt Iames ſayde vnto thoſe that he wrote his epyſtle vn<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>to, ye deſyre and ye haue not, that ye deſyre, ye enuye and ye haue in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dignation one towardes an other and ye can not obteigne, ye fyght, ye warre, and haue not, becauſe ye
<pb facs="tcp:173926:73"/> aſke it not, ye aſke and receyue not bycauſe ye aſke it amyſſe, that ye maye ſpende in your voluptuouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes. To ſtande long in this thing, the tyme wyll not ſuffre me, but onlye this I wyll ſaye, that where as we ſtande, neade of many thyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges all ready, we ſhall ſtande nede of moo: if we wyll not heare hym crye and be dylygente in cryenge agayne to hym: and that not onelye in mouthe, but alſo in harte, yea and in lyfe: For what ſhall it proffytte vs to call god oure father, yf we wyll not vſe oure ſelues as louynge chyldren. What ſhall it auayle vs, to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſyre hym to delyuer vs from all euell, when as we oure ſelues wyllyngely, do fall hedlynges in to all wyckedneſſe. But nowe lette vs heare what he cryeth by Iohn<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, he cryeth thus: prepare and
<pb facs="tcp:173926:74"/> make readye the waye of oure Lorde. There be two wayes of our Lord, one is, whereby he com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>methe vnto vs, an other is where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by we goo vnto hym: and bothe theſe muſte be prepared of vs, after that we haue hard his voyce, as touchinge the fyrſte, the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dycyon and ſtate of man is ſo my<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerable,<note place="margin">Roma. 5,</note> that he of hym ſelfe can not ones thyncke of the prepa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rynge of this waye, nor of goynge vnto god. But the loue, mercy, and gentylneſſe of god towarde man, is ſo great, that he wyllyng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lye of hym ſelfe dothe come vnto vs: yea beynge his extreme enemy<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>es, ſerchynge yf he can haue anye entraunce into our hertes, but yet althoughe that he commeth of his owne free wylle vnto vs withoute all oure deſertes, we muſte moly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fye, yea and open our hartes, that
<pb facs="tcp:173926:74"/> he maye haue enteraunce, or elles he wyll departe agayne: he ſaythe him ſelfe. <hi>Ecce ſto ad oſtium, &amp; pulſo.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Apoc. 1.</note> Beholde I ſtande at the doore, and I knocke, and yf anye manne wyll heare my voyce, and open the doore I wyll come into hym, and I wyl ſuppe with him. Marke he ſayeth he ſtandeth at the doore of oure hartes, and knocketh, but nowe it is oure parte, to heare his voyce, and open oure doores, for if we ſo do he wyll (as he ſayth) come in, yf we wyll not, he wyl not bruſt the doores, and come in, whether we wyll or no, for he wyll ſaue no man agaynſt hys wyll. But nowe it is neceſſarye to knowe howe we ſholde open this doore, this ſame Iohn<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> dothe teache vs ſayenge.<note place="margin">Math. 3.</note>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Penitentiam agite vitae prioris.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Do penaunce for youre olde lyfe, for penaunce, yf it be perfaict with
<pb facs="tcp:173926:75"/> the three partes whiche be well ynoughe knowen, Contrycyon, confeſſyon, and ſatyſfactyon. It is of ſuche ſtreyngthe, that by Chryſte, it makethe a manne of the ſeruaunte and bondeman of the deuyll, the ſonne and heyre of god and fellowe heyre with Chriſt,<note place="margin">Luc. 3.</note> it makethe alſo (yf that by it hye hylles be pulled downe, and lowe places be exalted, yf croked wayes be made ſtreyghte, and ſharpe wayes made playne) the harte of man of a fylthye lake, or denne of ſynne and the deuyll, a temple and dwellyng place of the holye Ghoſte. But nowe when as this way is thus prepared by pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce we muſt beware &amp; take hede y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> we do not retourne agayne into Egipt, but rather remember what we be now become, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> is that we be made the temple of the holye ghoſt
<pb facs="tcp:173926:75"/> whiche temple if any manne pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phane, god wyll deſtroye him,<note place="margin">1. Cor. 3.</note> we muſt therfore nowe ſtreight enter into the other waye, whiche is ſpo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ken of in the Pſalme:<note place="margin">Pſal. 118.</note> 
               <hi>Beati imma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culati in via.</hi> Bliſſed be they that be vndefyled in the waye, that is to ſaye, that walke in the way of our Lorde, in the latter ende of this verſe, it dothe appere bothe what the way is, and alſo how we ſhold vſe our ſelues in it. Fyrſt the way is y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> lawe or co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>maundementes of god, whiche yf we kepe will bryng vs to the heue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ly kyngdome where as Chriſt is gon before to prepare vs a place, but we muſte marke that the Pſalmiſte ſaith, that we muſt walke in the waye, for we be ſtraungers &amp; haue not here a by<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dynge citie,<note place="margin">Hebre. 13.</note> but we loke after one to come: wherfore we muſte not ſtande ſtyll, but rather walke and
<pb facs="tcp:173926:76"/> go forther from vertue to vertue. Now if the tyme wold ſuffre me, I wolde ſpeake here of the faſhy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of men now in theſe dayes, for many there be, as I thynke whiche do not walke in this way, but do ru<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ne as it were in a circuit, and maye be lykened to a dogge that runneth in a whele, whiche ſtyll goeth and laboreth, &amp; when he maketh an ende, he is euen where he begonne. And ſo I do feare that men do in theſe dayes: theyr tyme goeth, and they growe in age, and yet loke how they ly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued the laſte yeare, &amp; euen ſo they lyue this yeare, and ſo wyll do the nexte: nothyng at all increaſynge in vertue nor godlynes, but do as vittelars vſe to do, whiche take bread and drincke of bakers and brewers, to a daye, not payenge money in hande, but tayle with
<pb facs="tcp:173926:76"/> them: &amp; when the day of payment cometh, they paye theyr money, &amp; ſtrike of the olde tayles, and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gynne agayne to tayle of newe. And eue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſo do we: we be very bold with god all the yeare longe, and tayle with hym tyll lente comme: and then we be confeſſed, kepynge abſtinence for a tyme, and receyue the holy Sacrament, and ſo ſone as Eaſter is paſt, we begyn euen to tayle of newe, and fall agayne to our olde kynde of lyuyng. But ſuch be not theſe that Dauid cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led in this place, happy: for they do not walke vndefyled in this way. This ſame Dauid doth tea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>che in an other place ſaieng:<note place="margin">Pſal. 18.</note> 
               <hi>Si mei dominati non fuerint tunc immacula<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tus ero:</hi> yf that the deuell &amp; ſynne did not ouercome me, then I ſhall be vndefyled. He that wyll ende<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uour him ſelfe to walke thus in
<pb facs="tcp:173926:77"/> this waye, muſt take the counſell of Dauid in the firſt Pſalme, that he do reme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>bre and meditate this lawe bothe daye and nyghte, and be lyke vnto a tree that is ſet nigh vnto a ryuer to brynge forth fruit in dewe tyme. And not onely he muſt remembre this waye or lawe in his mouthe, in ſpeakynge and talkynge of it, but alſo he muſte haue it in his harte. And then as Dauid ſaithe in an other place. <hi>Non ſubplantabuntur greſſus eius.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Pſal. 26.</note> He ſhall be ſure that he can not be ouerthrowen. yet not withſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dynge Chriſte ſaith that this is a narrowe and a ſtreyght way, and that there be but a fewe that finde it: For although that there be no other thynge, yea not the deuell hym ſelfe, that can pulle vs out of this waye, or ouerthrowe vs a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaynſt our wyll yet not withſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dynge,
<pb facs="tcp:173926:77"/> we our ſelfes if we walke not circumſpectly, may ſoone fall, &amp; go out of it: Wherfore we muſte prouide for thre thyngꝭ. Fyrſt one to teache vs this waye, Seconda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ryly a candle to ſe how to walke in it. Thyrdely and laſte a ſtaffe to holde vp when we comme to ſlyp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per places. It is god that muſte teache vs this way, vpon whome we muſt diligently call with Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uid, and ſay:<note place="margin">Pſal. 24.</note> 
               <hi>Vias tuas domine de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſtra mihi, &amp; ſemitas tuas edoce me</hi> Lorde ſhewe me thy wayes, and teache me thy pathes. The candel that muſte gyue vs lyght, is the ſcripture of god, as Salamon witneſſeth ſayenge:<note place="margin">Prouer. 6</note> 
               <hi>Mandatum lu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerna, &amp; lex, lux.</hi> The commaunde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of god is a candell, and the lawe is lyght. The ſtaffe that we muſt walke by, is to lyue ſoberly, ryghtuouſly, and godly. For as
<pb facs="tcp:173926:78"/> Iohn<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſaith there lyeth in our way thre ſtumblyng ſtones,<note place="margin">Tite. 2.</note> that is the concupiſcence of the fleſhe,<note place="margin">1. Iohn<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. 2</note> the con<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>cupiſcens of the eyes, whiche is couetouſnes, and pryde. And if y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> we ſtumble at none of theſe thre, we ſhall walke ſaue in this waye, whiche thyng we ſhall do, yf we obſerue and keape y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> thre vertues before mencyoned whiche muſt be gotten and preſerued by thre mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes: To lyue ſoberly, the meane is faſtynge. To lyue ryghtuouſly, y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> meane is to gyue almes. To liue godly, y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> meane is to be occupyed in prayer: which thynges yf ye di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligently obſerue, and kepe: we ſhal walke vndefiled in this way, and ſo come home agayn at the length to our heauenly countrey, frome whence we were baniſhed and exi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led. There euer to continewe, with the fathe, and the ſonne, and the
<pb facs="tcp:173926:78"/> holy gooſte: to whome be laude, and prayſe in worlde with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out ende. Amen.</p>
         </div>
         <trailer>Finis.</trailer>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="colophon">
            <p>¶Imprynted at London in Alderſgate ſtrete by Io<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hannes Herford, at the coſtes and charges Robert Toye dwellynge in Paules church yarde, at the ſygne of the Bell. Anno dn<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>i 1545.</p>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
